<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true, and exact relation of the difference between Mr. Christopher Cisner, one of the pastors of the French Church in London, and others of the consistory thereof, and John Jurin senior, merchant, a member of the same church Wherein the treacherous dealings towards the French churches in England, and erroneous doctrine asserted by Mr. Cisner, and his obstinacie, either to maintein, or retract it, are discovered: as also, the unjust defending him therein by that consistory, and their irregular proceedings against Mr. Jurin, are palpably objected to publique consideration. For the vindication of the said Mr. Jurin. By publique licence.</title>
            <author>Jurin, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 210 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87438</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895816</idno>
  <idno type="VID">153451</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240909106</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing J1213A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205179</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895816</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99895816e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87438)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153451)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2365:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true, and exact relation of the difference between Mr. Christopher Cisner, one of the pastors of the French Church in London, and others of the consistory thereof, and John Jurin senior, merchant, a member of the same church Wherein the treacherous dealings towards the French churches in England, and erroneous doctrine asserted by Mr. Cisner, and his obstinacie, either to maintein, or retract it, are discovered: as also, the unjust defending him therein by that consistory, and their irregular proceedings against Mr. Jurin, are palpably objected to publique consideration. For the vindication of the said Mr. Jurin. By publique licence.</title>
                  <author>Jurin, John.</author>
                  <author>D'Oneau, John.</author>
                  <author>Cisner, Christopher.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 87, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by William Bentley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: John Jurin Senior.</note>
                  <note>Includes letters signed by Jurin and Christopher Cisner, and testimony signed by John D'Oneau.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Newberry Library, Chicago, Illinois.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Cisner, Christopher --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">French Protestant Church (London, England) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153451:1"/>
            <p>A true, and exact RELATION OF THE Difference between Mr. <hi>Christopher Cisner,</hi> one of the Pastors of the <hi>French Church</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> and others of the <hi>Consistory</hi> thereof, and <hi>John Jurin</hi> senior, Merchant, a Member of the same Church.</p>
            <p>Wherein the treacherous dealings towards the <hi>French Churches</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and erroneous Doctrine asserted by Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> and his obstinacie, either to maintein, or retract it, are discovered: As also, the unjust defending him therein by that <hi>Consisto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and their irregular proceedings against Mr. <hi>Jurin,</hi> are palpably objected to publique Consideration.</p>
            <p>For the vindication of the said Mr. <hi>Jurin.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>By publique Licence.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>William Bentley.</hi> 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:153451:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153451:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Reverend, and Worthy the Pastors, Elders, and Deacons of the <hi>French Churches</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> who are Members of our <hi>Colloquie,</hi> Grace, and peace to them be multiplied through our Lord <hi>Jesus Christ.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>(Reverend, and Worthy Sirs.)</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHereas you are the onely <hi>Representative</hi> of our severall <hi>Churches,</hi> sitting in each particular <hi>Consistory;</hi> Out of whom, according to the good, ancient, and laudable Custome of our Church-government, fitting Members are to be chosen and deputed by Letters of Deputation to assemble together, whereby to compose, and form a <hi>Colloquie,</hi> which is the super-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendent power of our Churches, and hath been honoured, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged to be so, and is our onely naturall, and proper judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catory, and Judges within our selves for the ordering and regulating of all our Church affairs, for and during a very long succession of years; I have therefore to you, (As my dutie requires me,) made this present <hi>Dedication</hi> of the following <hi>Remonstrance:</hi> Wherein I do not doubt, but upon your serious perusall and Consideration, my impulsive necessity to publish the same to your View, will be most evidently manifest. To the end I might justly vindicate my self from the false, and scandalous Aspersions of <hi>Mr. Christopher Cisner</hi> &amp; <hi>Mr. John Baptista Stouppe,</hi> and some of their Adherents, Members of the <hi>Consistory</hi> of <hi>London.</hi> And therefore give me leave, I beseech you with as much brevity as I can, to declare unto you the motives, and grounds that induce me hereunto.</p>
            <p>Some few Members of the <hi>Consistory</hi> of <hi>London</hi> taking part
<pb facs="tcp:153451:3"/>with <hi>Mr. Cisner,</hi> whereby to cover, and conceal his manifest Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and injuries, committed by him against the Doctrine and Discipline of our Churches, and to scandalize and abuse me toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with <hi>Mr. Elias Delmey</hi> (our pious and faithfull Pastor,) and <hi>Mr. Daniel Fervacques</hi> (amongst many other Fathers of Families) in particular, did the last year, (as if it were the Act of the whole Church, when in truth it was but some part of the <hi>Consistory</hi>) print and publish a Book both in <hi>French</hi> and <hi>English: Wherein (among <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> many other Calumnies, and reproachfull Termes.) they unworthily charged Mr.</hi> Delmey <hi>to have raised an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Quarrell between Mr.</hi> Cisner, <hi>and my self and Mr.</hi> Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacques <hi>And instead of labouring to appease it, he had kindled, and venomed it; joyning with us two in a foul Accusation which <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> set forth against Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> and upholding the Quarrell with us to the very last. Although the <hi>Consistory</hi> had declared it to be false, and ill grounde<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> Hereby designing to justifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, in outward, and common Appearance; by casting a Blemish, and disgrace upon us as of we should be offenders and enormous persons For clearing whereof and that our selves are innocent, and their Book false, and slanderous I commend the ensuing, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to your Censure Whither <hi>Mr. Cisner</hi> dealing treacherously with our <hi>Colloquie</hi> in the year <hi>1646</hi> by falsifying, and betraying his Deputation from them in the Case of <hi>Doct<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> De Laune,</hi> and <hi>Mr. D'asigny</hi> at <hi>Norwich,</hi> as is so palpably discovered in this Book be not worthy of due Reproof, And when as also he delivered false and erroneous Doctrine in the Pulpit, and also maintained it to me and <hi>Mr. Fervacques</hi> upon the Exchange, for which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired him to give me Christian satisfaction, by proving or denying his position he instead thereof returning ill words to me at that place by traducing <hi>Mr. Delmey</hi> and others with my self without cause, Calling us that party that troubled the Church and declining to give me any satisfaction at all. And I thereupon replying that the troubles of the Church, proceeded from one of that party, that was sent to <hi>Norwich</hi> for the peace of that Church but betrayed it, he then gave me the Lie, &amp; accused me to the <hi>Consistory</hi> of <hi>London</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:153451:3"/>that I had called him Traitor on the Exchanger And thereupon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing summoned to attend them, produced my Author <hi>Mr. Fervacques</hi> who confirmed his Report made to me of <hi>Mr. Cisner</hi>'s treachery, and owned the business, offering to prove it, and accordingly hath fully done it by valid and sufficient Testimony, and indeed from <hi>Mr. Cisner</hi>'s, own hand writing. Yet nevertheless some Members of the <hi>Consisto<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> would still unjustly hold me on with <hi>Mr. Fervac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques</hi> to maintain my words: Notwithstanding since that he owned and maintained them, I ought then by all Laws and reason to be discharged from further Attendance or prosecution thereupon. And that they might the more injurio<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sly deport themselves they wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly acquitted <hi>Mr. Cisner</hi> notwithstanding the proof and evidence of <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> offence and suspended me from the Sacrament of the Lords Supper Refusing all offers propositions and terms of putting the difference to a Methodicall Enquiry and judgement, severall times made and proposed by me to them, according to our Discipline, and government that your selves in <hi>Colloquie</hi> as my proper judges, might determine the same. And for that Cause I made my protest against them and appealed to all our Churches in <hi>Colloquie:</hi> Which by their indirect means was prevented from forming at <hi>London</hi> in <hi>January 1655</hi> and also from assembling at <hi>Centerbury,</hi> As of common right they should have done the 12<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>May 1656.</hi> And instead thereof they laboured to introduce and bring in a <hi>Coetus</hi> of the strangers Churches in <hi>London</hi> onely conjoyned with themselves, and dissolving all brotherly Communion with some of our Churches, most unnaturally would have set the <hi>Coe<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> up to be the naturall judges of all our differences in our Church in <hi>London:</hi> Being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectlie opposite to the verie nature and constitution of a <hi>Coetus;</hi> which is an assemblie, merelie, and onelie for consulting and order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Civill affairs, and hath no power or influence at all upon matters of Church government, since the establishing of our <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquies</hi> for almost eighty years together: And by this Device would destroy and overthrow the use of our <hi>Colloquies,</hi> and in the end, and bent of their intentions, quite root up our government and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish it totallie out of our Churches. But at length, by his <hi>Highness</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:153451:4"/>gracious favour we obtained the libertie of a <hi>Colloquie,</hi> which was vigoroustie opposed even before his <hi>Highness</hi> person, by <hi>Mr. Stouppe</hi> and others of <hi>Mr. C<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sner</hi>'s Abetters Before whom I did expect that my greivance should have received a due h<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aring and full Relief. But as you will herein fully discover (besides many of your own personall knowledges thereof,) that by the irregular Actions of onelie five persons deputed to sit in <hi>Colloquie</hi> in <hi>August</hi> and <hi>September 1656.</hi> (who, being the less number of the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes</hi> of all our Churches concerned to sit, and refusing to receive two of our Churches, could not regularlie act as a <hi>Colloquie</hi> rightlie constituted according to our government,) all my hopes became frustrate and all our Differences left without redress; Whereby such a grand and notorious division hath happened amongst us as renders us Contemptible to the nation, wherein we live; for that being brethren of one common profession, and so ought to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace, we by our own unhappy dissention are accounted, even as common enemies one against the other. Which in truth I must confess had been (by Gods blessing) prevented, and happilie pacified, if those persons in the <hi>Consisto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> who have been so active with <hi>Mr. Cisner</hi> had inclined to the Advice of <hi>Mr. Florantine <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ainturier,</hi> (a godlie ancient and well experienced Elder,) and not have abused their brethren that dissented from them, as did <hi>Mr. Vancourt,</hi> and four Deacous with them in <hi>Consistory.</hi> And indeed I cannot complain against the whole <hi>Consistory</hi> in generall, but the Major part, who are lead away by <hi>Mr. Cisner</hi> and <hi>Mr. Stouppe,</hi> and three or four leading men more onely.</p>
            <p>But for as much <hi>(Reverend and worthie Sirs,)</hi> as that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of all the Churches in generall, as well as my own Case in particular, is so sad and lamentable, and that our government hath been at tempted to be pull'd down, and a new form introduced, to our verie great scandall &amp; prejudice, and dishonour of our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessors, and that also contrived onelie by some few disorderlie, passionate, and unexperienced persons, and merelie out of wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
<pb facs="tcp:153451:4"/>and obstinacie to countenance, and abett, and protect from ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice a notorious Delinquent, (as <hi>Mr. Cisner</hi> is,) to the great dishonour of God, and trouble of our Churches, I humblie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beseech you to quit your selves like good Christians, by inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing your Aid, Councell, and advice, whereby to preserve, the honour and Authoritie of our <hi>Colloquies</hi> from ruine, and destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and also to put your judgements into action, that a <hi>Colloquie</hi> may be speedilie called, and regularlie formed, or some other means foundout; Whereby justice and right may be done to everie one grieved, and oppressed, and such Censures be imposed on persons offending as the merit of their fact shall justlie deserve: Which for my own part I am verie readie and willing to submit unto, if I shall be judged an offender. That thereby the Churches may be re esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished in peace, and tranquillitie and the Discipline, and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof defended, and protected against all opposition, and from confusion amongst our selves. And these things I humblie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you to lay to your hearts, and activelie prosecute, and pursue, that, what by the Religious care of our reverend, and worthie Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessors was in the worst of times asserted and maintained, may not by our negligence, disrespect, indifference, or carelesness be deserted, and forsaken in the times of greater light, and manifesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of truth.</p>
            <p>I should not upon any termes have made my self (being a private person, though verie much injured,) so publick as to be visible in Print, were it not, that my sincere and heartie love and affection to the order, good government, and reunion of our now sadlie distracted Churches do move me thereunto; Albeit that the scandals and hard Censures past upon me, vented even by one, that I hold to be a godly man, but partiall in his judgement, had been sufficient cause to move and stir up anie man that desires to hold faith and a good conscience, and to walk as becomes the Gospell of Christ, to vindicate himself by all due waies and means. And more especiallie when as the parties, that appose and gainsaie him, upon all Accompts where by to prevent and obstruct the verie ordinarie and direct Rule and
<pb facs="tcp:153451:5"/>means of Redress, shall be so wilfull and obstinate as to refuse and reject all Propositions and offers of peace and settlement whatsoever. And that this is my case, you will manifestlie discover in reading this Book: Which for your better Information I present unto you.</p>
            <p>And with all desire you to be pleased to consider one verie mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Circumstance in the Case of <hi>Mr. Delmey,</hi> which is this: That at the verie time, when <hi>Mr. Delmey</hi> was suspended from his office of Presidentship, there were (as I am informed), but seven Elders of thirteen in the <hi>Consistory</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> whereof three Elders oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and voted against his suspension, whereby it was carried but by one vote of the Elders. This I offer, that the Churches may be advertised, how few persons in number have begun and carried on the ungodlie procedings against <hi>Mr. Delmey;</hi> who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver (as I have heard) had anie Complaint made against him, by anie of the Congregation either for Doctrine, or manners: For which there have been divers Complaints made against <hi>Mr. Cisner,</hi> as being erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous in Doctrine &amp; scandalous in his Conversation; Nor have anie opposed <hi>Mr. Delmey,</hi> but the pluralitie of the <hi>Consistory.</hi> Which Theseech you well to consider in reference to your Observation upon the Book latelie printed, concerning <hi>Mr. Delmey</hi> and themselves, published by the Fathers of Families; that when it shall please God to instruct your hearts for the assembling of a <hi>Colloquie,</hi> or finding out some other means of deliverance of our poor Churches from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stress, and violation, you may be the better prepared to act, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine concerning our present differences. And that Almightie God will be mercifullie pleased to direct your Counsells, and Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for the welfare of our Churches, whereby Religion may flourish in its puritie and the power of Godliness be continued therein against all Error and Corruption, to the glorie of God, and honour of our Christian profession, is, and shall be the praiers of him, who is.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sirs,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your servant in all brotherly<lb/> duty, and Communion.</hi> John Jurin <hi>Senior.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153451:5"/>
            <head>A true, and exact Relation of the Difference between Mr. <hi>Christopher Cisner,</hi> one of the Pastors of the <hi>French-Church</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> and others of the <hi>Consistory</hi> thereof, and <hi>John Jurin</hi> the elder, Merchant, a Member of the same Church.</head>
            <head type="sub">For the Vindication of the said Mr. <hi>Jurin.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Churches of the <hi>French</hi> Tongue, inhabiting in <hi>England,</hi> being assembled by their Deputies, and Proxies at <hi>London,</hi> in the year, 1644. in a <hi>Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie,</hi> (the Capitall, and supreme Convention for the Rule, and Government of those Churches, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ancient, and laudable Usage, and Custome of the Discipline thereof,) did by their Act fully, and unanimous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agree to suppresse the Observation of all such daies, as were heretofore commonly called, <hi>Holy-daies;</hi> Which before that time were commemorated by those Churches; But afterwards they did decline to solemnize them; Nor have they been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served by any of them, till within a twelvemonth last past; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting onely, that the <hi>French Church</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> (contrary to the said Act, and merely out of a perverse, and precipitate Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion against Ecclesiasticall Orders, designing to be distinct by themselves from all our Sister-Churches,) have lately intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced and required the Observation of such Dayes: Albeit that the said Act was confirmed, and established in another <hi>Colloquie</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> of the said Churches, in the year, 1654. At which time, some of the Consistory of the Church in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:153451:6"/>did, in Order to the making a Proposition by their Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to that Colloquie, propose in their Consistory, That Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-daies might be again set up. Which motion was opposed by Mr. <hi>Elias Delmey,</hi> (one of the Pastors of that Church,) and some others in the Consistory; But by the Majority of voices, that Proposition was ordered to be made to the Colloquie; Whereby to have their explanation.</p>
            <p>Upon occasion whereof, Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> took an opportunitie to treat of that subject; Demonstrating the unlawfullnesse of observing such daies: At the hearing whereof, it was obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by some, that Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> was very impatient; who assoone as Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> had given the blessing, did openly before the Congregation averre, <hi>That</hi> Mr. Delmey <hi>had preached a sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sermon.</hi> Which was such a pertinacie, and insolent affront from a <hi>Minister</hi> to a <hi>Minister,</hi> that it is without example in all the Churches of the <hi>French</hi> tongue in <hi>England,</hi> that ever can be memorized. But at the time of the meeting of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie in <hi>September</hi> 1654. all differences were accorded in the Church; yet at that Convention the Deputies of London desired, that the Colloquie would explain the Act, made in 1644. concerning the putting down of holy daies; alledging that they had no intent to keep them. Whereupon the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie declared, <hi>That that Act did prohibite unto the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of our tongue in England, the publique exercises on holy daies; But did not condemne, as superstitious, or Idolatrous those Churches, that practised the contrary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not long after the dissolution of that Colloquie, Mr. <hi>John Doneau</hi> junior of <hi>Norwich</hi> (being in <hi>London,</hi> in company with Mr. <hi>Daniel Fervacques,</hi> and others,) And discoursing about that Injury offered to Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> by Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> was verie much discontented, saying, <hi>It is no marvell; for hee that will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray a Church, will make no conscience to trouble a godly Minister of the Church:</hi> And so related the particulars of what Mr.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153451:6"/>
               <hi>Cisner</hi> had done, to Mr. <hi>Fervacques;</hi> who communicated the same to <hi>my selfe;</hi> Not-withstanding which, (the said difference being so newly reconciled,) Although Mr. <hi>Cis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi>'s offence was, (as hereafter shall be described,) a most egregious Act of treachery, Mr. <hi>Fervacques,</hi> and <hi>my selfe</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved to conceale, and entombe it in oblivion, for the peace of the Church.</p>
            <p>But the implacable spirit of Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> (who will not live quietly with Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> his religious, and faithfull Brother,) could not long confine it self in the limits of Moderation: and therefore Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> some time afterwards preaching on a Lord's day, upon the 21<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
               <hi>Section</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> Catechisme, <hi>touching Repentance,</hi> was controverted, and opposed by Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> in an other irregular manner; for that on the Wednes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day following Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> complained to the Consistory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst that sermon; suggesting, that Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> had prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched against his Colleague Mr. <hi>John Baptista Stouppe</hi> (ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Pastor of that Church;) whereunto Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, that he intended no such matter; for that hee had studied his sermon, before he had heard Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> preach the Lord's day in the morning: But this answer would not pacifie the Consistory; who being instigated by those other Pastors, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded to make an Act of Consistory forthwith against Mr. <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mey,</hi> to oblige him against his conscience; unto which hee could not in duty, and good conscience acquiesce. But the irregularity of that complaint will be clearly manifested, if the custome and practice of the French Churches be duly consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, which is; <hi>That as soone as a Sermon is ended, the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters and Elders repair to the Vestry, or Consistory-house; and if a Minister hath delivered any thing not well understood, or wherewith any person is dissatisfied, it is presently propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to him, while it is fresh in memory, to explain and distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish.</hi> Which was not required of Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it may be more then conjectured, that Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153451:7"/>his party in the Consistory complotted, not to impeach him for his sermon presently after its delivery; supposing he could not afterwards make so positive a defence, as he might have done immediately, when the matter was obvious to the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Hereupon the differences recovered new strength, and vivacitie; which being perceived by my selfe, and meeting Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> and Mr. <hi>La Roche</hi> (one of the Elders) at the Royall Exchange in London, I, (together with Mr. <hi>Fervacques</hi>) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved to conferre with them; But by no means to cast oyle on the fire incensed, but extinguish it rather with the water of longanimity, and discretion, and in truth, to say not so much as a word, which should administer a just offence. And thus resolved, wee there accosted them; My selfe affirming, that I was verie much greived, there should bee new divisions touching Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi>'s Sermon, upon repentance; but Mr. <hi>La Roche</hi> alledged, that his affaires would not permit him to stay, and so departed. Wherefore I did tell Mr. <hi>Cisner, That I heard</hi> Mr. Delmey, <hi>and in my judgement his doctrin was sound and good;</hi> whereto he replyed, <hi>It was sound:</hi> upon which I demanded, <hi>Wherefore then they made such a severe Act against him;</hi> to which Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> retorted, <hi>Because that he preached against</hi> Mr. Stouppe, <hi>whose doctrine was also good and sound:</hi> upon which I did desire Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> to declare, <hi>why such a severe Act should be made, since both the Pastors had preached the truth; and how, and wherein</hi> Mr. Delmey <hi>had failed:</hi> Who said, <hi>in the manner of his Sermon;</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly fell out into a passion of anger, saying, <hi>that</hi> Mr. Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mey, <hi>and his partie troubled the Church:</hi> Whereupon I intreated him to forbear such expressions <hi>of parties, which ought not to be in the Church of God; And as they were all one Body, so they ought to be all of one minde:</hi> But Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> seemed to defend it, alledging, <hi>that in the Church of Corinth, there was a party for</hi> Paul, <hi>another for</hi> Apollo, <hi>and another for</hi> Christ: Who
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153451:7"/>being questioned, <hi>Whither they were commended, or reproved for it,</hi> answered, <hi>that they were reproved;</hi> Wherefore with much fervency I besought him, <hi>that thenceforth he would desist to use such Terms of Division; for thereby the Church would never be in quiet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore at the same time, and place, I had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> about a sermon, which he had prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched; wherein hee had asserted, <hi>that there was hypocrisie in the Law;</hi> telling him, <hi>that I beleived there was a Mistake in the Auditors, and that he was not well understood by them.</hi> To which Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> replied, <hi>that he did utter som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to that purpose:</hi> And then said, <hi>That the law was an hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite, and promised that which it could not perform;</hi> &amp; moreover, <hi>If one was born in the state of innocency (as Adam was,) and had kept the Law from point to point, yet he should not be saved by it.</hi> Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which I returned, <hi>That it was verie strange doctrine, and</hi> I <hi>was much unsatisfied therewith.</hi> Wherefore Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> said, <hi>That perhaps</hi> I <hi>was ignorant and knew not what hypocrisie was.</hi> Which (truely) I profest, <hi>I did not:</hi> upon which Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> began to inform mee, <hi>that there were two sorts of Hypocrises,</hi> But abruptly declined; Passionately alledging, <hi>That</hi> I, <hi>and my partie were the troublers of the Church:</hi> which <hi>I</hi> had good cause to disclaime; and to affirm, <hi>That the troubles of the Church were from that partie, that was sent down to</hi> Norwich <hi>to settle the peace of that Church, and betrayed it.</hi> Upon which Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> gave Mee <hi>the Lie,</hi> and said <hi>they were all liars, that affirmed it.</hi> But I saying, <hi>What if it be proved? who then shall be the Liar?</hi> Wee departed one from the other without further discourse.</p>
            <p>Whereupon Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> complained to the Consistory. <hi>That I, and</hi> Mr. Fervacques <hi>had called him traytor on the Exchange:</hi> To which they gave credit, and ordered Us to appear before the Consistory; And upon summons
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153451:8"/>
               <hi>Wee</hi> attended; The Consistory chargeing <hi>Ʋs</hi> with the premisses; And saying, <hi>That the Papists made Song's of it, and what a great Scandall, that was to Religion.</hi> Whereupon I desired to be informed, (before I answered that false Accusation,) <hi>Whither the Discipline was changed within two years past:</hi> Whereto Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> (then President) replyed, <hi>It was not to the matter.</hi> But at the length I saying, <hi>It should be no hindrance to my answer, and pressing</hi> as before; Mr. Stouppe said, <hi>He thought the discipline was not altered.</hi> Then I made reply, <hi>That if it was so, they had broken the Discipline; for that they, ought not to have called</hi> Mee, <hi>and</hi> Mr. Fervacques <hi>before the Consistory, till they had used the common and accustomed Practice of the Governement; which is according to the Doctrine and advice of our Lord and Saviour</hi> Jesus Christ <hi>in</hi> Mathew, 8: Chap. 15.16, 17. verses: <hi>Desiring them earnestly to peruse the</hi> 5<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
               <hi>Article of the</hi> 3<seg rend="sup">d</seg> Chap. <hi>of the booke of the Discipline concerning Elders;</hi> which they refused: Wherefore insisting to declare the Passages of the discourse between Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> and <hi>my selfe</hi> at the Exchange; Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> required mee <hi>to come to the Fact;</hi> Iterateing those expressions severall times. Whereupon <hi>I</hi> being interrupted, said to the Consisto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>that if</hi> I <hi>was not suffered to speake,</hi> I <hi>had nothing to doe there.</hi> And then they gave <hi>mee</hi> leave to proceed: which I againe assaying to doe, was still neverthelesse obstructed by Mr, <hi>Stouppe.</hi> Wherefore perceiving Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi>'s unjust designe to suffocate, and stifle the truth, I applied to the Consistory, And said.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:153451:8"/>
            <p> SIRS!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BEING that you will not suffer</hi> Mee <hi>to relate what passed,</hi> I say, <hi>that the accusation of</hi> Mr. Cisner <hi>is false:</hi> For he said unto mee, <hi>That I and my partie were the troublers of the Church:</hi> I said to Mr. <hi>Cisner, Noe: it was not I, nor they that he called my Party, that troubled the Church; But it was from that party, that were sent to</hi> Norwich <hi>for the peace of the Church, and betrayed it:</hi> Mr. Cisner said, <hi>That I lyed, and all those that said it.</hi> I told him, <hi>if it be proved, who then will be the Liar, and so we parted.</hi> S<seg rend="sup">IRS</seg>! <hi>His conscience reproved him so strongly, that he tooke it to himself; when as it was said of the Company. For there were five persons besides himself; And why should he take it to himselfe, but that he knew himself to bee guilty.</hi> And further I said to the Consistory: <hi>If</hi> Mr. Cisner <hi>had had the Patience to have demanded of mee, whom</hi> I <hi>meant, No doubt, but that</hi> I <hi>should have told him.</hi> Whereupon the Company in Consistory desired to know my meaning; And thereunto <hi>I</hi> answered, <hi>that I meant</hi> Mr. Cisner, <hi>and him only; for that</hi> I <hi>was fully perswaded, that the rest of the Gentlemen had done their duties according to their Commissions.</hi> Wherefore the Company re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired <hi>mee</hi> to tell them, <hi>From whence I had received that Information; I</hi> answered, <hi>that</hi> I <hi>had it from</hi> Mr. Fervacques <hi>(then and there present.)</hi> And Mr. <hi>Fervacques</hi> being demanded, <hi>If he had made such a Relation to mee,</hi> affirmed positively, <hi>that he had so done, and all the matters were true; And that he did speake it only of</hi> Mr. Cisner.; <hi>justifying himself in telling mee the Particularities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr. Cisner</hi> hereupon <hi>called God, and the Holy Ghost to be his witnesses, that the said accusation was false; and that wee had forged it, and were inventors of Lies, and tellers of Lies.</hi> Of which Invocation, and his scandalous Expressions, <hi>Wee</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153451:9"/>the Company to take notice, and observe. Who said to mee, <hi>that I must yet prove my accusation;</hi> Albeit that Mr. <hi>Fervacques</hi> had owned, and asserted it before them; And thereby by the Law of God, and the Lawes of this Land, I ought not to have been further enjoyned to make any other proof; for that when I had produced my Author, there nothing more remained, but that the Author himself should proceed to mainteine, and averre his Information, and not my selfe. Upon this Mr. <hi>La-Roche,</hi> (one of the Company,) said: <hi>that I ought to be discharged by the Lawes of this Land:</hi> But Mr. <hi>Stouppe,</hi> (then President,) affirmed, <hi>that by the Lawes of</hi> France <hi>I ought not:</hi> Which being so opposite to common equity and natural reason, cannot be solidly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to be the usage, or practice of any Civil, or well constituted Governement: But if it be the custome of <hi>France,</hi> (not being approved, or admitted in <hi>England,</hi> where our Laws are just and right,) it is however no waies obligatory, or astrictive to any persons of the <hi>French</hi> Churches in <hi>England:</hi> For that they are not bound to any Method of procedings by their Ecclesiastical Discipline, other then accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the word of God, and the Lawes of reason, founded thereupon: Which to all <hi>Societies,</hi> and <hi>Assemblies,</hi> (professing <hi>Christianity,)</hi> ought to be their absolute <hi>Rule,</hi> and <hi>prescription,</hi> without <hi>variation,</hi> or <hi>declension.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After all this the Company demanded of Mr. <hi>Fervacques, Of whom he had received his said Information,</hi> Alledging <hi>that it must be proved; and required of him to tell them, in what time it might be done;</hi> who answered, <hi>that his evidence was farr distant from</hi> London, <hi>and it could not be produced sodainly.</hi> Wherefore they passed an Act of Consistory, and allotted him a month's time: Upon the Reading of which Act (at Mr. <hi>Fervacques</hi> request,) It appeared to mee,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153451:9"/>that although I had produced my Author, and pressed in Justice to be disobliged from further attendance; The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany had neverthelesse engaged me equally with Mr. <hi>Fervac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques,</hi> to make good that information contrary to all right reason, and good Conscience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I shall here insent the following</hi> Article <hi>of our Discipline be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-mentioned.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="document">
                        <head>The 3. Chapter, <hi>(of the Discipline,)</hi>
                        </head>
                        <head>Concerning the Duty of the Elders; (<hi>And the</hi> Ministers, <hi>and</hi> Elders <hi>are the Body of the</hi> Consistory.)</head>
                        <head>The 5th Article.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>None amongst them shall bring his neighbour before the</hi> Church, (<hi>that is to say, the</hi> Consistory) <hi>for to accuse him of secret or particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar faults, unlesse he hath first advertised him according to the Order, prescribed by our</hi> Saviour <hi>in the</hi> 18th Chapter <hi>of Saint</hi> Mathew. <hi>Which they shall endeavour may be observed, as well for themselves, as also for the particular Members of the</hi> Church.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>By this the Reader may plainly discern, how wrongfully the <hi>Consistory</hi> behaved themselves towards me, in admitting an Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation against me by Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> contrary to the word of God, and the constant and uninterrupted Custome and practice of all our Churches; For they ought not to have called me before them, (according to the tenor of the said <hi>Article</hi>) untill that the Elder of Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> and mine Elder had used their joynt endeavour to have pacified and reconciled the difference between us; And then, (having first tried those means, and no Reconciliation procured,) those two Elders ought to make their Report to the <hi>Consistory,</hi> who (if they saw it good,) might thereupon have sent for me, and not before. And thus their irregular pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedings in breaking the Discipline of our Churches, have been the cause of all the difference herein related) between them and my self.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:153451:10"/>
            <p> Being prohibited to make a full Declaration of the truth of the Discourse at the Exchange, between Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> and my self before the <hi>Consistory,</hi> I therefore sent the Original in <hi>French</hi> of the ensuing translated Copy of a Letter by Mr. <hi>Peter Bar,</hi> (one of the Elders,) to Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> which was delivered unto him, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>London <date>the 16th: of February. 1654.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>Mr. Cisner.</salute>
                     <salute>SIR!</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I <hi>Am very much unsatisfied, and cannot begin quiet, till you explain, and prove your saying to me touching the Law: you, told me,</hi> It was an Hypocrite; For it promised that which it could not perform: And that under the Law, if one was born in the Estate of innocencie, as <hi>Adam</hi> was, and had kept the Law exactly from point to point, and fulfilled it; Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthelesse he could not be saved by it. Sir, I <hi>had come to you to have received satisfaction; But I feare, that we might fall again into new disputes. Therefore to prevent it, I desire that you would bee pleased to send it mee in writing: And that will be the meanes, that I shall not misunderstand you: having not else: onely waiting your Answer. I rest.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours, who desires to be enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened in all truths.<lb/> John Jurin <hi>Senior.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>To which Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> declined to return any Answer: The cause whereof is palpable to the Reader, That if he could have defended his Position or Assertion by the principles of true <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Religion,</hi> he would not have been so averse to refuse an answer to his Christian brother. But to leave the cause (whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153451:10"/>presumption or ignorance,) to Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi>'s own breast, wherefore he with-drew himself from giving due satisfaction unto mee; The Reader shall, (if he please,) further observe the deportment of the said Consistory toward me. For they unjustly summoned mee with Mr. <hi>Fervacques</hi> before them, (the moneths time being near expired, by them limited for proving the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusation against Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> as aforesaid.) Who attended them; And Mr. <hi>Fervacques,</hi> (having received an Answer of his Letter, by way of Justification of the Accusation against Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> from Mr <hi>Doneau,</hi> whom he had sent for according to the Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storie's Order,) did extract so much thereof, as related to Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> and reading it to the Consistory, left it with them, and with-drew. Whereupon after some Consideration by them had thereupon, they called both my self and Mr. <hi>Fervacques</hi> in again; Telling us, that Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> was not nominated, but onely a <hi>Gentleman</hi> indefinitely: By which they would not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> to be meant; But required further Testimony: Which was offered, so soon as Mr. <hi>Doneau</hi> conveniently came to <hi>London,</hi> which he promised he would do with all expediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Supposing with all that which was in his Letter might have sufficed; Albeit he had not particularly named Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> to avoid (if possible,) his publick disgrace: When as the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it self, (of which he was accused,) was to himself most evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and notorious.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> and his Company, (labouring to make all the Covers, and shrouds they could, whereby to cover his unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full practice, in falsifying his deputation; And taking advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the absence of Mr. <hi>Doneau,</hi>) did again summon me, and Mr. <hi>Fervacques</hi> before them in Consistory; Who appearing, were required to make good our further evidence; The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory seeming very much displeased, that Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> should lie so long under an Accusation, without any proof thereof; Threatning us to proceed against us according to the Discipline. Wherefore Mr. <hi>Fervacques</hi> assured them, that Mr. <hi>Doneau</hi>'s
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153451:11"/>occasions had obstructed his coming longer, than he expected; But that he would be in <hi>London</hi> very shortly. And for my part, (Who at my last Appearing's had not interposed at all to speak, but left all to Mr. <hi>Fervacques,</hi>) but perceiving my self to be threatned in like manner with Mr. <hi>Fervacques</hi> by the Company, I desired them to beware, least they repented at lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure; Considering, that I ought to have been discharged for the reasons aforesaid.</p>
            <p>Thus having done with the Company at that present, I as yet perceiving no answer from Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> to my former Letter, had penned a second in readiness; Intending to deliver it my self to him; Which being profered, Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> refused to accept it, saying, he would neither receive any Letter from me, nor give me any answer. Wherefore I applying those uncivill expressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the Company said, I would open the Letter; and so I did, and left it before them in <hi>French;</hi> The translated Copy whereof followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>London <date>the 4<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of April. 1655.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>Mr. Cisner.</salute>
                     <salute>SIR.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THe</hi> 16<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
                     <hi>of</hi> February <hi>I did write to you, desiring you would be pleased to give me satisfaction of that, you told me touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Law, that it was an Hypocrite, promising that, which it could not perform; And also, that if one was born in the state of Innocencie, as</hi> Adam <hi>was, and had kept the Law from point to point, nevertheless he could not be saved by it.</hi> Sir, <hi>I did not doubt, but that you would have sent to mee your Affirmation, proved by the word of God; As every one ought to do, the one to the other; But especially the Ministers of the Gospel, when they have spoken that,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153451:11"/>which one doth beleeve to be to the dishonour of God, and contrary to his word. Then I say, one ought in duty to given satisfaction. Saint</hi> Paul <hi>saith:</hi> Wherefore the Law is just, and the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment holy, just, and good. <hi>It is then no Hypocrite! And Saint</hi> Paul <hi>saies also,</hi> Not the hearers of the Law are justified before God; But the doers of the Law shall be justified; <hi>And God saies,</hi> Do this and thou shalt live. <hi>God is truth it self: God hath spoken it, and will he not do it? God hath promised it, and will he not perform it?</hi> Sir, <hi>In speaking so lightly of the Law of God, which he pronounced with his mouth, and wrote with his own fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, it is a great sinne.</hi> Sir, <hi>I hope this will incite you to give me an Answer; And upon which I wait, and rest.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>John Jurin <hi>Senior.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Letter being left by me, as aforesaid; And presently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards meeting with Mr. <hi>D'obey,</hi> (one the Elders,) at the Exchange, I desired to know, if the Company had read it; Who replyed, that they had not; But onely he and another of the Consistory had perused it, and put it into the boxe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doing any thing further thereupon. Wherefore I pressed the Company again to read it, by Application to, and by my own Elder, and Mr. <hi>La Roche</hi> to them made; And therein to order, what should be just, and right: Which being propounded, their Result was, that Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> should give me satisfaction, when the matters of the said Accusation (then in difference) were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined between them, and Mr. <hi>Fervacques.</hi> This Answer being so strange, and egregiously unjust, occasioned, nay in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed necessarily enforced me to dictate another Letter, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the Consistory, and to present it in person; Which I read to them in the Originall in <hi>French;</hi> The translated Copy whereof followes in the words hereafter expressed, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:153451:12"/>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>London <date>the 24th of April. 1655.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>Gentlemen, and honoured Brethren.</salute>
                     <salute>SIRS.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THe Cause of my coming to you at present is, because that to this present, I cannot receive satisfaction from</hi> Mr. Cisner, <hi>of that he said to me concerning the Law,</hi> that it was an Hypocrite, promising that which it could not perform: <hi>And he also said, If one was born in the state of Innocencie, as</hi> Adam <hi>was, and had kept the Law from point to point, yet he should not be saved by it.</hi> Sirs, <hi>You know the last time, that I was with you here in</hi> Consistory, <hi>at the end I presented to</hi> Mr. Cisner <hi>a Letter, and he would not take it, saying also that he would not answer it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Seeing that therefore, I opened the Letter in your presence, and laid it down before you; hoping that you would have read it, and ordeyned something thereon: but meeting</hi> Mr. D'obey <hi>on the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, I asked him if the Company had read my Letter: He said, No: but be and another had read it, and put it into the Boxe. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering, that there was nothing done in that, which so greatly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured God, I thought it was my duty, that by all lawfull means satisfaction might be given. Therefore I desired my Elder</hi> Mr. Tainturier, <hi>and</hi> Mr. La Roche, <hi>that they would desire the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, that they would be pleased to read my Letter, which I directed to</hi> Mr. Cisner <hi>in the presence of the Company; Seeing that he would not receive it, nor give any anie answer. The Proposition hath been made, and the Companie's Answer was, that there should no An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer be given, till the difference be decided of the Accusation against</hi> Mr. Cisner. <hi>I have proved the Accusation by</hi> Mr. Fervac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques, <hi>and he maintain's it; And</hi> Mr. Fervacques <hi>hath proved it by</hi> Mr, Doneau, <hi>and doubts not, but that he will be here shortly, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153451:12"/>will maintain it to his face. Then it will appear, If</hi> Mr. Cisner <hi>ha's not held on the part of</hi> Mr. D'asigny <hi>against his Deputation.</hi> Sirs, <hi>Seeing that</hi> I <hi>had proved the Accusation,</hi> I <hi>am clear from that false imputation of</hi> Mr. Cisner; <hi>saying, that</hi> Mr. Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacques, <hi>and</hi> I <hi>have invented those lies; And that we were Tellers of lies, and Chiquaneurs. Seeing that it is false, therefore it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine's, that</hi> Mr. Cisner <hi>must give me satisfaction of his slander; And in time, and place</hi> I <hi>shall require it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sirs, <hi>Me thinks! the reason that you bring for delaying of sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, hath no weight; Because if the Acccusation of</hi> Mr. Cisner <hi>was true; and that</hi> I <hi>had inventea it, (as he said,) falsely: Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theless in the first place, the Glory of God ought to be more dear to us than our own ho<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>urs, nay</hi> I <hi>say, more dear than our own lives. Therefore</hi> (Sirs, <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>suffer me to say to you, without offending you, That the office of Ministers and Elders is, aswell to see to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, as to manners and scandals: And when such doctrine is maintained, that is to the dishonour of God, Then you ought to use the power, that God hath put into your hands for his glory, and to do it in the first place.</hi> Sirs, I <hi>hope you will not take it in evil, that</hi> I <hi>do importune you again, seeing it is for the glory of God, and that which I do require of you, ought not to be denied me in good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science; desiring you, that you would be pleased to take it into your Considerations, and to ordain that which shall be for the glory of God. Attending your answer, I remain,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your affectionate servant for<lb/> the glory of God.<lb/> John Jurin <hi>Senior.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Letter, and request being thus read by me to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory, Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> (their President,) without any Methodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Proposition of a question to the Consistory, or mature deliberation by them upon the Contents thereof; But onely
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153451:13"/>in an irregular manner did solely of himself propose to me, That if I would promise to submit to that, which they should ordain, they would tell me their result. Whereto I made reply, That <hi>I presented my self to the Company, and not particularly to</hi> Mr. Stouppe, <hi>and it was not for him to give me Answer, before the matter was proposed to the Company, and their advice given thereon:</hi> Which at length he acknowledged, desiring me to with-draw, till the business was debated: Which being done, and afterward called in again, Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> said to me, that if I would promise to submit to what they had ordered, They would tell me their Resolution: Otherwise they had nothing to say to me. By which in truth, (As I told the Company) It is evidently demonstrative, that they could sing no other song, but Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi>'s: Which they rather unworthily preferred to gratifie, than to vindicate the glory of God, so much concerned in the difference: Which was not in my power, nor indeed ought it to be of any other good Christian desired that a business of so great an Import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and Concernment should be attempted to be buried in forgetfulness: And yet how manifestly, and plainly it may be collected, that by the Companie's Compliance with Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi>'s Note, they more gratefully designed to conceal Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi>'s offence, and secure him from due Censure and Reproof, than that the glorie and honour of God should be extolled, and advanced, though it was by Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi>'s finall shame, and Reprobation: Which by all true Christians, and pious profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors of the Gospel, ought first to be sought, and permitted, rather than that the Majesty of God should be detracted in the least <hi>Jod,</hi> or tittle of any of his Attributes, or Excellencies. And can there be a greater detraction, and evill speaking, than to undervalue, and disprize the Justice, and goodness of God in giving our forefathers (the seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi>) so holy, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153451:13"/>just a Rule, Command, and prescription, As he promulged, and published on <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> with so much manifestation of his power, and great glory to <hi>Moses;</hi> So that there was a radiation, and reflection thereof in the very face of <hi>Moses;</hi> to the great Amazement of the <hi>Israelites</hi> his brethren. Besides if we consider the equity, and admirable Reason of the <hi>Decalogue;</hi> And what Testimonie and respect our blessed <hi>Saviour</hi> gives it in his <hi>holy Gospel,</hi> that he came not to destroy the Law, but to fulfill it; And from thence doth by way of Exposition, and Illustration, most justly deduce those Exquisite, and most holy morall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, and Axioms for the ordering and governing of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians life, (As are contained in his Sermon on the mount,) with a sure promise thereunto of eternall salvation; We cannot in reason, or Religion otherwise conclude, then that those Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions of Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> touching the Law of God, with so much disdeigne, and disestimation, merit, and deserve the detestati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and abomination of all good Christians; And that he ought either publickly to renounce, and disclaim such dangerous, and erroneous Opinions; Or for his pertinacy to be made a publick Example, for the satisfaction of those, that walk worthy of their vocation; and conviction of others, that are, or may be seduced by such evil doctrine, and pernitious Opinions.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithstanding, the Consistory answered me that they had nothing more to say to me; unless I would explicitely, and generally submit to them, as aforesaid: And Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> said, <hi>that I was a Rebell against the Church, for not submitting to them:</hi> Whereto I answered, <hi>that I must have of the faith of the Church of Rome to believe, and add faith to that which I did not know; And that I praised God, I was better instructed: And that their office was to satisfie those that desired satisfaction, without bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to condescend to any thing they did not know:</hi> In such manner did this Consistory proceed towards me, as the Bishops heretofore would have done by their Oath <hi>ex officio,</hi> which they would have imposed on the Clergie with an <hi>Et caetera;</hi> Binding
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153451:14"/>them by an Implicite faith to acquiesce in such Canons, as the Convocation should institute, Be they what they would, before they should have known one letter thereof. A design so destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to the Liberty of a good Conscience! That had it pleased God permissively to suffer it, It would soon have enthralled the godly Ministery of this Land, in a more than Egyptian Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage: But as God of his infinite mercie suppressed the Authors, and Fomentors of such a mischief complotted against his own Inheritance; So it hath pleased God in this private difference between Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> and my self, so farre to disanimate the Monster of that Project, As that it is not to be questioned by a Judicious Reader, but that without an Herculean adventure, if he rightly compare the Circumstances in this Treatise, he may overcome the Hydra of this subject, without a <hi>Non obstante,</hi> or any other defence or exception.</p>
            <p>The said Consistory behaving themselves towards mee in such a partiall, and prejudiciall manner, as before I have rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, so that they would not condescend to give me any satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction at all. I therefore desired them to resolve mee, <hi>what was the Reason, that the Reader in the</hi> French Church <hi>doth read every Lords day the Ten Commandments, assoon as the Minister is going into the Pulpit, and all the people stand with their hats off, In case that the Law be an Hypocrite?</hi> Conjecturing that by this Interrogation, they would have been incited to return mee an answer. But as men affrighted with some sodain, and unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Accident, they looked one upon the other, and gave mee not a word of answer. And thereupon I took my leave and departed.</p>
            <p>At length being in daily expectation of the coming of Mr. <hi>John Doneau,</hi> the very Letter it self, (which Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> did write to <hi>Norwich</hi> concerning Mr. <hi>D'asigny,</hi>) came by Gods good Providence, to the hands of Mr. <hi>Fervacques; Wherein he desired the Parties that were engaged with</hi> Mr. D'asigny, <hi>that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153451:14"/>they would be pleased to vouchsafe him a Testimony, that he well behaved himself in his Deputation from our Colloquie.</hi> Whereas in truth he was sent down in favour of Mr. <hi>De Laune,</hi> and his party, against Mr. <hi>D'asigny</hi> by our <hi>Colloquie,</hi> with other De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties, to put in execution the sentence of the <hi>Colloquie,</hi> against Mr. <hi>D'asigny</hi> for his obstinacy &amp; unworthiness. And if Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> had fairly, and honestly deported himself, according to his charge, It had been most congruous, and proper for him to have sent to Mr. <hi>Delaune</hi> for a justification, (in whose behalf he was deputed,) then to those who were his adversaries, and under the Censure of the <hi>Colloquie.</hi> But by the Sequell it will evidently appear, that Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> did of set purpose treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously adhere to Mr. <hi>D'asigny,</hi> whereby to illude, and frustrate the sentence of our <hi>Colloquie</hi> against him; And by his perfidious discovery of th<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> counsells and secrets of the <hi>Colloquie,</hi> and his fellow Deputies to Mr. <hi>D'asigny,</hi> render all their Actions, and Designs for the peace of the Church in <hi>Norwich,</hi> altogether fruitless, and ineffectuall.</p>
            <p>Wherefore to proceed in such a Tract, as the necessary Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances lead and induce me, I shall acquaint you with the further ill behaviours of the Consistory of <hi>London,</hi> whereby they might the more facilly prevent the Detection of Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi>'s offence: Which I hope will be constructive, even by the weakest capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, and apprehension; And manifestly also discover their neglect of Duty and respect to his Highness and the State; To whom they ought with all gratefull submission for their favour, and protection, to render all due obedience, and compliance to all their Acts and Ordinances of State with all readiness, and alacrity.</p>
            <p>Then to the matter! On a <hi>Saturday</hi> night Mr. <hi>John Doneau</hi> coming to <hi>London,</hi> Mr. <hi>Fervacques</hi> gave notice thereof the <hi>Lords day</hi> following after evening Sermon; And that he would attend the <hi>Consistory</hi> the <hi>Wednesday</hi> after, being a <hi>Consistory</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:153451:15"/>day. But for asmuch as that a Fast was appointed by his <hi>Highness</hi> to be kept on <hi>Thursday</hi> following, (Of which the <hi>Consistory,</hi> (As they ought to have done,) took no notice at all;) And (as may be conceived probable,) through no good affections to the Observation of, and conformity to his <hi>Hignesss</hi>'s Order, and Appointment, did make no publication on the <hi>Lords day</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,) The <hi>Consistory</hi> thereupon afterwards bethinking them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, (But upon what grounds, is not known, but onely to themselves,) did afterwards order, that each Elder should go in his quarter, and give advertisement to the Members of our Church, that the Sermon, (which of usuall Course, was to have been on the <hi>Wednesday,</hi>) was put off, and deferred till the <hi>Thursday,</hi> which was set a part for a Fast, as aforesaid. And Mr. <hi>Tainturier</hi> (the Elder of Mr. <hi>Fervacques,</hi>) coming to him, and giving him an intimation according to the said Order, of the Adjournment of the meeting till <hi>Thursday,</hi> did hereupon inform that Elder, that Mr. <hi>Doneau</hi> had appointed to be gone out of <hi>London</hi> towards <hi>Norwich</hi> on that <hi>Thursday</hi> morning; For that his business, being very urgent, required him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from thence; Desiring Mr. <hi>Florantain,</hi> that he would be pleased to come that immediate after-noone, and hear what he could say: But he declined so to do; Proposing rather, that some body else might undertake it. Which being related to Mr. <hi>Doneau,</hi> he said, that through the extremity of his oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions, and affairs, he could not by any means possible stay in <hi>London</hi> any longer, whereby to attend the <hi>Consistory:</hi> And therefore that he might declare his Testimony, to as much effect, as lay conveniently within his power, (with respect had to his own private occasions, which he might not in good reason prejudice, being under no Coercive power, but merely in a friendly manner desired to assert, and averre a matter within his own knowledge,) Mr. <hi>Doneau</hi> did thereupon commit to writing the Relation of his evidence, (As hereafter shall be more expresly, and in terms set forth;) Which he sign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and subscribed with his own proper hand-writing in the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153451:15"/>presence of three credible Witnesses, (who have been, and are readie to justifie, and affirm the same to be true;) And deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered it with his subscription to Mr. <hi>Fervacques;</hi> On purpose that he might present it with all suitable opportunity to the <hi>Consistory,</hi> for the better manifestation, and confirmation of the truth of his Information concerning Mr. <hi>Cisner.</hi> And on that <hi>Thursday</hi> morning Mr. <hi>Doneau,</hi> having done as aforesaid, went from <hi>London</hi> on his journey to <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The same day Mr. <hi>Fervacques</hi> came to mee, and desired me to accompany him to the <hi>Consistory,</hi> that we might present to them the Testification of Mr. <hi>Doneau:</hi> But in regard it was a Fast day, I conceived it not so proper to attend them on such an occasion that day, advising him to defer that affair till the <hi>Wednesday</hi> after: And moreover Mr. <hi>Fervacques</hi> on that fast day had given notice to his Elder of the departure of Mr. <hi>Doneau</hi> from <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;</hi> And that by reason of his great haste to be at home, he had left the particulars of his knowledge in writing. And when <hi>Wednesday</hi> was come, We presented our selves to the <hi>Consistory,</hi> (Mr. <hi>Fervacques</hi> having delivered into my custody the Originall Letter of Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi>'s before expressed, and keeping to himself Mr. <hi>Doneau</hi>'s Testimony:) Where being come, and notice given of our attendance, the Company called for Mr. <hi>Fervacques</hi> to come in before them singly: But being they had obliged me at former times equally with him to make proof of the Accusation, I went in with him. No sooner was I before them; But Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> (their President,) <hi>desired me to with-draw, saying, they did not call mee in:</hi> Whereupon I replyed to them in words, <hi>Sirs. It concerne</hi>'s <hi>me, seeing that you would not dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge mee, but have kept mee on this business against all Justice and equity.</hi> Upon which the Company said, <hi>That if I would not with-draw, they had nothing to say to us: And we might with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw if we would.</hi> Perceiving thus their obstinacie, and pervers<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness I bethought my self, that it was better for mee to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw, then not to deliver in to them, what evidence we had
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153451:16"/>ready against Mr. <hi>Cisner:</hi> For it was their main design to have taken all advantages against us, whereby they might have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented the discovery of our proofs against Mr. <hi>Cisner:</hi> For which they would have gladly taken the occasion from my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusall to depart out of their presence: And thereupon I with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew my self. But I pray observe the Indifferencie, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice of the <hi>Consistory!</hi> Who as soon as I was gone out required of Mr. <hi>Fervacques</hi> to produce the Testimoniall of Mr. <hi>Doneau,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi>'s own Letter. He told them that I had that Letter; But delivered to them the Originall of Mr. <hi>Doneau</hi>'s sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription, with a Copy thereof; desiring them to compare, and examine them, and to return him the Originall; For that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved to keep: Both which Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> receiving and the Company delaying to read, or peruse them, Mr. <hi>Fervacques</hi> pressed them with much Importunity so to do. But they refused; Resolving, that Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> should compare them privately by himself. Which was so done by them, meerly to surprize Mr. <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacques,</hi> That they might the better keep secret the said Relation of Mr. <hi>Doneau,</hi> from the Company, As I conceive, or else they would have permitted it to have been read.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Fervacques</hi> hereupon came out from the <hi>Consistory,</hi> and told mee in what manner they had surprized him: And imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately they called for my self to come in. As soon as I was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, Mr. Stouppe <hi>desired mee to deliver to them</hi> Mr, Cisner's <hi>Letter.</hi> To which I answered, <hi>That if they would read it publickly before the Company, I would not onely deliver them the Originall, but a true Copy: But my resolution was, that when they had compared and examined that Copy with the Originall, I should willingly leave that Copy with them; But the Originall I would keep my self.</hi> Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> hereupon said to mee, <hi>that the Companie had ordered, that he should compare them privately by himself.</hi> I replied to him, <hi>That my address was to the Company,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:153451:16"/>and not to himself onelie: And what they required, or had ordered was against the practice of our Government, and the like was never heard of before amongst us: And therefore I would not deliver it in such a manner, nor unless it was read before the Companie.</hi> To this Mr. Stouppe returned, <hi>That the Companie had not so much time, as to read it.</hi> I answered, <hi>That could be no excuse; for if one read the Originall, and another took the Copy, It would be done in the tenth part of the time.</hi> Hereto Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> gave answer, <hi>that if he read the Letter, there would be disputing about it, and they had not time to do it.</hi> I made reply, <hi>That if that was the true reason, I for my part would promise not to speak one word so as they would presently promise to hear me, and</hi> Mr. Fervacques <hi>fullie to the matter, before they did proceed to the determination thereof.</hi> Which the Company did promise they would do, before they passed their sentence.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> hereupon pressed me again to deliver the said Letter, Which I told him, <hi>I was resolved not to do, unless it might be publickly read.</hi> Wherefore Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> perceiving my Resolution, <hi>praied mee, and</hi> Mr. Fervacques <hi>to with-draw:</hi> Which being done, Mr. <hi>Stouppe,</hi> Mr. <hi>Isaac De Lillers,</hi> and Mr. <hi>D'obey</hi> came out of the <hi>Consistory</hi> to us, and said, <hi>that the Company had sent them to read the Letter; Comparing the Copy with the Originall.</hi> Wherevpon we manifestly apprehending the unjust, and unreasonable Actions of the Company, which were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to all Precedents of times past, and that they had some indirect Design, and ayme in agitation, Whereby to save, and secure Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> from just Censure; But at length discerning no other remedie, We yeilded to those three persons, upon Condition, that before they did proceed in <hi>Consistory</hi> upon the business, they would hear what we could say: <hi>Which they faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully promised to do, and to grant us suficient time; which then they said they could not set apart.</hi> I then delivered them the said Originall, and Copy; They read, and compared them, and returned mee the Originall, <hi>Alledging that the matter was of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153451:17"/>great consequence, and at that present they could not consider of it. But before they did enter upon it, they would give us notice, and hear what we could say.</hi> We referred our selves to their own time,, <hi>desiring them in the mean space well to consider of the busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, as it was of great Concernment, and with drew.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I question not but the Reader will much admire, why the <hi>Company</hi> have acted, and mannaged this business contrary to all Rule, Order, and example within the Government of our Churches, and against all equity, and right reason; in stiffling and obstructing the ground and proof of the Accusation against Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> by not permitting them to be publickly read before them. And truely well he may! When as by their partiality, and too much affection to Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> (If ever they did read those particular Charges against him before the Company,) they never did resolve (I doubt) any thing thereupon without his advise; And it is not incompetent in reason to conceive, that he was affraid, that such a positive discovery, and proof of his offence, should be published to the Company, before such time, as that he had instructed, and secured his friends to his advantage, and gained time, and opportunity for them to fitt, and prepare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves with Arguments, and Expositions, whereby to justifie Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> from any Crime, or misdeed, or at least to construe, and interpret it with a more candid, and favourable Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentation, then in truth the just merits of his fact do deserve. And as it might have seemed strange to his friends at first; So the Company did take a singular, and remarkable Course, that they shoud never hear of it at all, As farre forth as they could possibly advise, or imagine: Or otherwise they would not have made such strange Resolutions, and orders; As before, and in this Treatise shal be manifested and declared.</p>
            <p>But before I shall further impart, and relate to the Reader the Transactions of the <hi>Consistory</hi> concerning Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> or my self, I hold it requisite to give him a perfect, and exact
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153451:17"/>Accompt of the miscarriages of Mr. <hi>D'asigny;</hi> (Whereupon he fell under the Censure and judgement of our <hi>Colloquie</hi> in the yeer. 1646: which was ordered by them to be put in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution by Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> and others; And which Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> for his part onely, did, as much as he could, attempt, (as before is hinted, and insinuated,) to render, and make it of noe pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, or effect:) As being the originall ground, and occasion of all the ensuing matters herein after contained, with as much brevity, as I can, not abridging the truth.</p>
            <p>And now, that the truth of particulars may be the more Methodically understood, I shall acquaint the <hi>Reader,</hi> that Mr. <hi>D'asigny,</hi> being in <hi>London,</hi> and not having any <hi>Pastor-ship,</hi> or charge in any of the <hi>French</hi> Churches in <hi>England;</hi> And being related in so<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e kindred or affinity by his wife to Doctor <hi>De Laune,</hi> (Paster of the <hi>French</hi> Church in <hi>Norwich</hi>) went down to <hi>Norwich,</hi> to give the said Doctor a visit: whither being come, the Doctor received him with much civility, and desired him to preach a Sermon for him to his congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: which he did with much satisfaction, and content to his Auditory. And after this the said Doctor, being aged, and very sickly was contented, and desired Mr. <hi>D'asigny</hi> to be helpfull, and assistant to him. Who being once admitted, and received, as a <hi>Coadjutor,</hi> by the <hi>Doctor's</hi> Consent, did, not long after so arrogantly, and aspiringly behave himself, as that he endeavoured to lay aside Doctor <hi>Delaune</hi>'s Ministery, and to gain the Church to himself. Which did occasion a debate, and Consideration of the matter by our <hi>Colloquie:</hi> Who at length for the peace, and quiet of the Church in <hi>Norwich,</hi> did order, that Mr. <hi>D'asigny</hi> should be <hi>Coadjutor</hi> to the <hi>Doctor.</hi> Mr. <hi>D'asigny</hi> hereupon having obtained such a foot-step into the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s Church, did so farre insinuate into the affections of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as that he made a Rent, and Schisme amongst them so wide, and distant, As that the greater part did ungratefully expell and put out the <hi>Doctor,</hi> (their ancient Pastor,) out of his Church. So that he was constrained with those, that of duty adhered
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:153451:18"/>to his Ministery, to meet, and assemble together in another place.</p>
            <p>Hereupon the <hi>Magistrates</hi> of <hi>Norwich,</hi> and the rest of the <hi>French</hi> Churches, Considering the quality of Mr. <hi>D'asigny</hi>'s Insolency, and Affront done to such an ancient Pastor, as the <hi>Doctor</hi> was, did assist him in his Application for redress to the Parliament; Who referred his Case, and Grieveance to a Committee: And they upon hearing the particulars thereof transferred the whole business to the decision and determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Colloquie,</hi> which should next meet, and convene for all our Churches; The Case being more proper for them to resolve, and adjudge according to our own Discipline, and Church Government.</p>
            <p>Not long after, <hi>viz.</hi> 12th of <hi>August</hi> 1646: A <hi>Colloquis</hi> of our Churches did assemble in <hi>London;</hi> And after a full bearing, and serious Consideration of the premisses, (amongst other matters then before them,) did pass this ensuing translated Act from the Originall in <hi>French,</hi> being the 87th Article of that <hi>Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie, viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This day was present, and the Articles read against</hi> Mr. D'a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signy, <hi>and the daies following examined, and proved: And after serious Consideration of the Discipline, and of all that doth belong to this business, the</hi> Company <hi>came to a finall Resolution, which was concluded on Munday the</hi> 17th <hi>of</hi> August, <hi>as followeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="document">
                        <head>Article. 87.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Considering the unruly carriage of</hi> Mr. D'asigny <hi>to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent</hi> Colloquie, <hi>held in</hi> London <hi>in</hi> May: 1644. <hi>(Which then made him worthy of Censure,) and the Continuation of it in an
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:153451:18"/>higher Degree, in continuing to resist all</hi> orders, <hi>both</hi> Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, &amp; Civill: <hi>From whence followed Disorders, factions, and tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults in the Church in the City of</hi> Norwich: <hi>And above all, shewing himself contumacious against the</hi> Colloquie, <hi>being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally called, (though all the differences of the said Church of</hi> Norwich <hi>have been returned by the honourable</hi> Committee <hi>of</hi> Parliament <hi>sitting at</hi> Westminster, <hi>to the determination of the</hi> Colloquie; <hi>Which also hath been signified unto him;) The</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany <hi>(after deliberate, and exact Examinations, aswell of all the Acts Authentick, as of the Magistrates, and higher Powers,) in the name, and by the Authority of our Lord</hi> Jesus Christ, <hi>declare the said</hi> Mr. D'asigny <hi>to be fallen from the title of</hi> Coadjutor, <hi>which was by the precedent</hi> Colloquie, <hi>(for the peace of the Church,) granted to him, and also unworthie of the holy Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisterie in the Church of</hi> Norwich: <hi>And besides do interdict him the execution of his Ministerie, not onelie in the Church of</hi> Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich, <hi>but also in the other Churches that are, or in those that may be of our</hi> Colloquie. <hi>The which</hi> Churches <hi>are by this present</hi> Colloquie <hi>expresly defended from admitting</hi> Mr. D'asigny <hi>into the exercise of the function of the holy Ministerie. And especially the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> Norwich <hi>is exhorted to put their hands to the execution of this</hi> Sentence: <hi>So that by that means, they may manifest their desire to continue in the</hi> Communion <hi>of our</hi> Churches, <hi>under the</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection <hi>of the</hi> King <hi>and</hi> Parliament.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>The <hi>Colloquie</hi> having made this foregoing sentence, did ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicicusly consider how it might be put in due execution. And at length they did elect, and choose five persons from amongst themselves to be sent to the Church of <hi>Norwich. viz:</hi> Mr. <hi>Philip Delmey,</hi> Pastor of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> Pastor of <hi>London,</hi> two Elders of <hi>London,</hi> and one of <hi>Canterbury;</hi> And all these five persons did fully undertake this their Deputation, promising to do their utmost endeavours, that the said sentence might be put in execution according to the true intent of the <hi>Colloquie.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:153451:19"/>
            <p> But the Reader shall now most palpably discern, that all the said Deputies, (excepting onely Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi>) did, (As by the sequel will appear,) honestly, and justly perform their duties; And that he, (and he onely,) was the man that betrayed his trust; And thereby as far as he could, perfidiously betray all the Churches of the <hi>French</hi> tongue in <hi>England.</hi> And this will most exactly be made evident, by the following translation of the Original in <hi>French</hi> of the Testimony of the said Mr. <hi>D'oneau</hi> against Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> which was not permitted by the <hi>Consistory</hi> of <hi>London</hi> to be publickly read, as is afore-mentioned. Which said Mr. <hi>D'oneau</hi> was an Elder in the said separated Congregation under Mr. <hi>D'asigny</hi> from the regular Church under Doctor <hi>De Laune</hi> in <hi>Norwich,</hi> And merely for love of the truth hath made the Publication of his knowledge, As followe<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="testimony">
                        <p>
                           <hi>I</hi> John D'oneau <hi>the younger do confess, and declare to whom It may, or might concern, That about seven, or eight years past, When the</hi> Deputies <hi>of the</hi> French <hi>Churches of</hi> London, <hi>and</hi> Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury, <hi>were sent to</hi> Norwich, (<hi>being lodged at the signe of the</hi> Blew-horse,) <hi>Mr.</hi> D'asigny, <hi>and</hi> I <hi>having had notice thereof, made our Address towards the said place. We sent to Mr.</hi> Cisner, <hi>(being in Companie of the said Deputies,) praying him to come to speak with some friends, which he did. Then Mr.</hi> D'asigny <hi>having saluted him, said unto him, That he must declare to Ʋs, all the ground of the business, for which they were Deputies to the Church, and that he should do it without concealing any thing. Whereupon the said</hi> Cisner <hi>answered, that he could not tarry for two reasons: First, because that he feared, that he should be suspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. Secondlie, that they were then upon the business, for which he was deputed, with other Circumstances: By which we heard, and understood that, which passed in their business, being in the Chamber joyning to theirs, where he left Ʋs, with promise to meet Ʋs on the morrow morning at an house in a place, called Sandling's Lodgings, behind the great Church by the River, (Being a place out of the way,) for fear he should he discovered in our Cempanie.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:153451:19"/>The which he did, (accordinglie, as he had promised us,) between seven and eight a clock in the morning. Where he continued untill about noone. Assoon as he met at the said place,</hi> Mr. D'asigny <hi>took</hi> Mr. Cisner <hi>by the hand and said to him,</hi> (Sir,) <hi>you must de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to us the ground of your business, for which you are come.</hi> He <hi>demanded of Mr.</hi> D'asigny, What man is that? <hi>Ʋpon which he answered, It is one of our friends: Fear not to declare all your business. Whereupon he declared to us manie things, that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties had order to propound to us, to the end to perswade us to yield thereto,</hi> (Which would take up too much time to relate.) <hi>And said to us that if in Case</hi> we <hi>would not consent thereunto, They would go by way of the Magistrate to perswade us to yield thereto: But if that would not do, Then that they should endeavour to do it, by way of a</hi> Committee. <hi>Whereupon there happened o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther discourse by the said Mr.</hi> Cisner; <hi>Who told us that we were not obliged to submit our selves; for they had not power to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain us to do it: Therefore we might keep us to our own Resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. This, (as above,) with manie other things, which he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared unto us, was concealed from the rest of the Brethren; fearing least he should be discovered; because if they had been spoken of, we could not have anie more understood the secrets, and that which passed in the</hi> Consistory <hi>of</hi> London, <hi>Which the said</hi> D'asigny <hi>rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to me, and told mee, that he understood them from time to time from Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>at</hi> London, <hi>with whom he did correspond. All this above said, although that it be verie true, I had not an inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to declare it; nor have I been required; But understanding the affront, that Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>did to Mr.</hi> Delmey <hi>openlie in the Church, I could not refrain my self to declare this; Which I had resolved to burie for ever.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Written <date>
                                 <hi>this eight of</hi> May. 1655.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <lb/>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Signed</hi> John D'oneau <hi>the younger.</hi>
                           </signed>
                           <pb n="30" facs="tcp:153451:20"/>
                           <hi>We under written do certifie, that this is the own writing and Subscription of</hi> John D'oneau.
<signed>
                              <list>
                                 <item>John Causton.</item>
                                 <item>David Dolley.</item>
                                 <item>John Fervacques.</item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>This Testification I submit to the Judgement, and Constru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Reader; And now I shall insert the translated Copy of Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi>'s own Letter, which he wrote to Mr. <hi>John De Hagen</hi> dwelling at <hi>Norwich,</hi> in <hi>French</hi> concerning Mr. <hi>D'asigny,</hi> and the business before intimated, As followeth. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>From London <date>this 10th of February, 1655.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>(SIR. and most dear Brother,)</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ALthough I have not had the honour for to converse with you in particular; Nevertheless the Report that hath been made unto me of your faithfullness, pietie, and sngular affection to the peace of the Churches, doth encourage me to write to you these few Lines, for to tell you my opinion, upon the matter of the Letter, which you have sent for answer unto that of my Church. Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie I must avow, that your</hi> Consistory, <hi>hath had some cause to be discontented for an apparent reproach, that was done to it; In regard that it appeare's by your Letter, the summ, that you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute unto him for his maintenance, and in doing all you can possible: For as the</hi> High Dutch <hi>Proverb saith,</hi> Where there is nothing, the Emperour himself looseth his right; And that no body is bound to an Impossibility. <hi>But if your</hi> Consistory <hi>take's the pains to consider, that our Letter doth not speak by Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but onelie by supposition, and report; Which hath been made to us by the Gentlemen, the Brethren of</hi> Mr. De Laune, <hi>your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:153451:20"/>yea who hath caused us to read divers Letters, which do witness his extream povertie; I hope It will make a favourable Construction of our expression, as it is convenient in the meekness of their charitie. In the mean time I pray you,</hi> (Sir,) <hi>to remember some things, which passed in your Church about seven, or eight years agone. Without doubt you remember, that the late</hi> Mr. Delmey, <hi>with some Elders were deputed towards your Church, for to deliver unto your</hi> Consistory <hi>the Sentence of the</hi> Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie, <hi>which was against him, &amp;</hi> Mr. D'asigny, <hi>(then your Pastour.) Now you all know, how holilie, and justlie I have carried my self in that Deputation, having not sought anie thing, but the good, peace, and edification of your Church; For which I continue my praiers unto God unto this day, as also for the other Churches, without ever to approve of the Instruments of violence, and the presumption of those; who under a pretence to govern the Churches, and to settle good order, do endeavour to bring in a tyrannous Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over the Inheritance of the Lord. But it is happened some moneths since after, to have served for an Instrument to reesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish, (By the grace of God,) the peace, and reunitement of the Church of</hi> Canterbury: <hi>For which all honest men do rejoice; except</hi> Mr. Delmey, <hi>(heire of his fathers violent passions;) That Satan hath raised me a great persecution, by means of the aforesaid</hi> Mr. Delmey, <hi>who for the Despight that he hath to see the reunite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the said Church, makes a new partie upon the ruine of our ancient Divisions: whereof the chief heads are,</hi> Mr. John Jurin <hi>the elder, and</hi> Mr. Daniel Fervacques; <hi>who, not contented to persecute me by Back-biting, have moreover reviled me openlie on the Exchange, in charging me to have betrayed the Church of</hi> Norwich, <hi>in the Deputation above-named; Although that my Conscience doth testifie by the holy Spirit of my Integritie, and that this monstrous Accusation of the Dragon is not onelie false, but ridiculous, and impertinent; Because they pretend the crime to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist in this, that I should have been the Cause of it (As they slander me,) that your</hi> Consistory, <hi>and</hi> Mr. D'asigny <hi>have persisted in their disorder, and rebellion. It is so that they speak: who otherwise
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:153451:21"/>without my Counsell, would have submitted themselves to the</hi> Colloquie <hi>and should have accepted of the sentence: But that your</hi> Consistory <hi>then (Of which</hi> Mr. D'asigny <hi>was President,) was the onelie Church of</hi> Norwich; <hi>From which</hi> Mr. De Laune <hi>separated, and was followed by some few persons, which might not, nor ought not to attribute to him the Name. How then could I have betrayed the Church; Of which, (According to what my Accusers say,) I was in the same, the Patron, friend, and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate. Where is, and what is the monie, that I have received of</hi> Mr. De Laune, <hi>and of his? What profit and utilitie have I received of your</hi> Consistory <hi>for this pretended and imagined treason? Where are the enemies, into whose hands I have delivered your Church? What are those mournfull Mischiefs, wherein my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell hath precipitated it? What is the revelation of those Admirable secrets, which hath fortified the Conductors in th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Disorders, and the Confusion? Truely as I know not any secret, which hath been committed to me by anie Company or by anie particular person, that may be; So I could not reveal anie secret, as the thoughts, that I had for the Church, were thoughts of peace. Also all the Counsell that I could have given to your</hi> Consistory, <hi>or to</hi> Mr. D'asigny, <hi>tended to perswade them to permit me the Pulpit, for to exhort the people to peace, and to dispose the one, and the other to a convenient submission to the first</hi> Colloquie <hi>ensuing, with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press promise, that</hi> Mr. D'elmey, <hi>and I should do in manner, that the sentence should be suspended, and that their Cause against</hi> Mr. De Laune <hi>shall be read over again, and examined anew; And that all Justice should be done them, without having anie regard to the Appearance of anie bodie. Nevertheless so it is, that because my Accusers have declared to my</hi> Consistory, <hi>that they will prove their Accusation by some Witnesses of</hi> Norwich; <hi>This therefore for fear that my Innocencie may not be made suspected by some false Testimonie, I have thought necessarie, most humbly to beseech you to do me the favour for to confer with your brethren, that then, (when I was in your Citie,) were in office, aswell of the Elders, as Deacons; Praying them instantly in my name to send me an
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:153451:21"/>Attestation, subscribed by them; In which it shall please them to give Testimonie to my Innocencie, and faithfulness: To the end by this means, untruth may have it's mouth shut. In doing this you shall acquit your Conscience, you shall aide the truth, exercise your Charity towards a faithfull servant of God, and shall oblige my Church, and me in particular for to pray to the Lord for your Prosperitie Corporall and spirituall: Seeing that I am, in expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Answer of your good grace, (after having recommended you to the saving grace of God.</hi> Sir, <hi>and most dear Brother.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your most humble, and most affectionate<lb/> Brother, and servant.<lb/> Signed.</hi>
                        <lb/> Cisner.</signed> Superscribed.<lb/>
                     <salute>
                        <hi>To Mr.</hi> John De Hagen <hi>dwelling at</hi> Norwich.</salute>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>I shall not need here to Paraphrase, or make any Exposition, or Commentary upon either the Testimony of Mr. <hi>Doneau,</hi> or Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi>'s Letter, as might well be expected: But for as much as I delivered to the <hi>Consistorie</hi> in person my Observations and consequent Deductions from the very matter and words themselves according to plain, and Grammaticall Constructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, upon and from the things themselves, I shall refer the Reader to the Consideration thereof; As he shall herein after find them particularly set forth. And now I shall proceed to declare the further Injustice, and partiality of the <hi>Consistory;</hi> Which the Reader may be pleased to observe, As the subject matters fall worthily under, and are submitted to his judgement, and Interpretation.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:153451:22"/>
            <p> Having delivered the Copies of Mr. <hi>D'oneau</hi>'s Testimony and Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi>'s Letter to the <hi>Consistory</hi> as aforesaid, Mr. <hi>Fervacques,</hi> and my self did, (As well we might,) expect that the <hi>Consistory</hi> would have appointed us a time, (according to their promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,) to hear what we could further say or alledge against Mr. <hi>Cisner:</hi> Which if they had done, had been but common and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Justice, and no more, than in honesty they ought to make good their promises: But as a clear and absolute violation and breach of both, and thereby of all requisite Civility, and humanity, they without ever calling us before them or giving us any notice, <hi>proceeded to a finall Determination, and Conclusion of the business; Acquitting</hi> Mr. Cisner <hi>from being guiltie of anie thing whatsoever, even of the least suspicion; And ordered</hi> Mr. Delmey <hi>to come to me, and</hi> Mr. Fervacques, <hi>and acquaint us, that they had considered of our accusation against</hi> Mr. Cisner, <hi>and passed their Judgement of Acquittall; Desiring him to perswade with us to submit, and yeild quietlie thereunto. And for the peace of the Church, all things should be buried, and forgotten:</hi> Which Message <hi>Mr. Delmey</hi> delivered to me, and as they requested him, <hi>he desired me to go to</hi> Mr. Cisner, <hi>and reconcile my self to him:</hi> But the news being so strange, and without Comparison, I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred much at Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> that he should undertake to be the Reporter of it, and indeed I was displeased with him, for gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any Colour to such Injustice.</p>
            <p>Hereupon Mr. <hi>Fervacques,</hi> and my self went to our Elder Mr. <hi>Florantine Tainturier,</hi> Signifying to him our Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Amazement, that the <hi>Consistorie</hi> should so lightly regard their reiterated promises to hear us before their Sentence given upon the matter: And that if we had lived amongst Heathens, they would not have dealt so unjustly with us; And hereupon we pressed him, That he would move the <hi>Company</hi> to hear us: Who did present our desires to them; And they returned answer, that they would hear us, and give notice to us when we should attend them. Which afterwards they did;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:153451:22"/>And we appeared before them: But instead of hearing us open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the <hi>Consistorie,</hi> Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> and some four or five more of the <hi>Companie</hi> desired us to go up with them into the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary: <hi>Whither</hi> being come Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> said, <hi>that it was necessary to think of some waies of Reconciliation; For they saw that the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visions increased in the Church; We answered, that it was our desire, upon a just and right ground.</hi> Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> demanded, <hi>what was our just, and right ground.</hi> We replyed, <hi>that we left it to the</hi> Consistory <hi>to propound to us; And if we found it for the glory of God, and the good of the Church, we should accept it.</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> asked me, If I would acknowledge Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> to be an honest man. I thereunto answered, that If I should so do, my Conscience would tell me, that I did lie. Wherefore Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> said <hi>that they would take it into Consideration, and we should hear from them:</hi> And so we parted. I expected from this Answer, that the <hi>Consistory</hi> would have advised, and considered of a way, to settle us in peace, and made some proposition to us; But they never did. By which it may well be concluded, that this was merely a Stratagem of Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi>'s to have drawn us to an acknowledgement, that Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> was an honest man, and so we should thereby have condemned our own selves. At length I having penned a Letter, and made some observations on Mr. <hi>D'oneau</hi>'s Testimony, and Mr. <hi>Cis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi>'s Letter, (which by reason of my hopes to receive the said Propositions, though readily prepared, I deferred to present;) And the <hi>Consistorie</hi> sending to me, and Mr. <hi>Fervacques</hi> to come and declare what we had against Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> We there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon appeared; And then I read this ensuing Letter to them in <hi>French,</hi> presenting the Reader with the Translation thereof, as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:153451:23"/>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>London <date>the 29th: of May. 1655.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>SIRS,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LAtely you were pleased to send unto me</hi> Mr. Delmey, <hi>for to persuade me to reconcile my self with</hi> Mr. Cisner. <hi>By that it seems unto me, that you do not hold me discharged of that I have said of</hi> Mr. Cisner. Sirs, <hi>It seems unto me, that I have justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied my self from what</hi> Mr. Cisner <hi>imputed unto me, because that I have produced from whom I had it, and that he doth acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to have told it me; so that he doth justifie me, that I am not the Inventor of it. And I say,</hi> I am no Inventor of Lies, nor a Chiquaneur, <hi>as</hi> Mr. Cisner <hi>imputed to me before you.</hi> Sirs, <hi>seeing that you do not hold me discharged, I am resolved, (by the Grace of God,) to justifie my self; for I will not betray my Innocency to cover the Hypocrisie, and unfaithfulness of another. Therefore we delivered on the</hi> 16th <hi>of</hi> May <hi>unto the</hi> Consistory, <hi>the Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of</hi> Mr. Doneau <hi>against</hi> Mr. Cisner, <hi>signed before witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and also the Letter of</hi> Mr. Cisner, <hi>which he wrote unto those, that held with</hi> Mr. D'asigny, <hi>for to obtain from them a Testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie to justifie him. It seems unto me, that both the above-said do prove amply, and clearly, that</hi> Mr. Cisner <hi>hath betrayed the Church of</hi> Mr. De Laune, <hi>and also the</hi> Colloquie; <hi>and spake un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily of them in outragious language. If this be suffered; where is our Government? In this he hath done more, than ever the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops did in time past; for I have not heard, that they did so vilifie such an Assembly, and spake unworthily of the dead, and of the living.</hi> Sirs, <hi>I hope that you have read the Testimony of</hi> Mr. Doneau, and Mr. Cisner's <hi>Letter in the presence of all the</hi> Company; <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though you would not suffer it then to be read, but that</hi> Mr. Stouppe <hi>must read it by himself. This hath not been the practice of the times past.</hi> Sirs, <hi>me thinks! to clear the things before you, it is needfull, that I do repeat unto you the beginning of this difference; for when you called me first before you, you would not suffer me to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:153451:23"/>declare it, but</hi> Mr. Stouppe <hi>interrupted me, and said,</hi> To the fact, To the fact! <hi>so that I was not permitted to relate it. And now it is necessarie to give you a true Relation of what passed: I seeing</hi> Mr. Cisner, <hi>and</hi> Mr. La Roche <hi>walking together on the</hi> Exchange, <hi>I resolved with my self to speak with them, to see if I could do something to allay the new begun differences, touching the Sermon of</hi> Mr. Delmey <hi>upon the</hi> 21th <hi>Section of the Catechisme, concerning Repentance. At the verie instant,</hi> Mr. Fervacques <hi>came to me, and I told him, what I intended to do, in speaking with those Gentlemen, and to cast water upon the fire begun, and not oile, and that I was resolved not to speak any thing, that might give just offence. So we went unto them, and having saluted them, I said</hi> (Sirs) <hi>I am verie sorrie to understand; that new differe<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ces have arisen in the</hi> Consistory, <hi>upon the Sermon of</hi> Mr. Delmey, <hi>on Repentance.</hi> Mr. La Roche <hi>said, his business called him away, so that he could not stay any longer, and so took his leave, and away he went. I said unto</hi> Mr. Cisner, <hi>that I did hear</hi> Mr. Delmey, <hi>and in my judgement, that which he preached was sound and Orthodox, and according to the word of God: he told me, his Doctrine was sound: Then I said unto him, why have you made such a severe Act against him? he said because that he had preached against</hi> Mr. Stouppe. <hi>I asked him, if</hi> Mr. Stouppe <hi>had preached the Truth: he said, yes; Then I said, if both of them have preached the Truth, then</hi> I <hi>see no just ground for such a severe Act of sentence against him.</hi> I <hi>prayed him to tell me, wherein he did fail: he said in the manner:</hi> I <hi>asked him in what: he thereupon became angry, and said that</hi> Mr. Delmey <hi>and his party troubled the Church:</hi> I <hi>prayed him not to keep up the names of parties in the Church; for so long as they retain names in the Church, it is to uphold parties, and that ought not to be in the Church of God; for they ought to be, (as it were,) but one Soul, as they be but one Bodie.</hi> Mr. Cisner <hi>seemed to maintain it, for he produced that Passage of the</hi> Corinthians, <hi>and said, that there was for</hi> Paul, <hi>and</hi> Cephas, <hi>nea, and a party for</hi> Christ. <hi>Ʋpon that I asked him, if the</hi> Corinthians <hi>were praised for it, or reproved; he said, Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:153451:24"/>Then I said, seeing they were Reproved, we ought not to retain names, and praied him, that he would not use it so often, as he did use to do: And further told him, that</hi> I <hi>had heard that he had preached of the Hypocrisie of the Law: saying that</hi> I <hi>thought, that he had not preached it, but that there was some mistake, and that he was not well understood. Then he told me, that he had preached something like it, and also said that the Law was an Hypocrite, promising that, which it could not give, or perform; and that more over, if any one was born in the estate of Innocencie, as</hi> Adam, <hi>and had kept the Law from point to point, and fulfilled it, yet he could not have been saved by it.</hi> I <hi>told him, that Doctrine was very strange Doctrine, and that I was very much unsatisfied to hear such Doctrine from him. He said to me, it may be you are ignorant, and do not unders<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>and what is Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisie.</hi> I <hi>did Confesse that</hi> I <hi>was ignorant, but my desire was to learn. And then he began to say, that there were Two sorts of Hypocrisie, and proceeded no further; but was angrie, and said, that it was</hi> I, <hi>and my partie, that troubled the Church.</hi> I <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon said, no not</hi> I! <hi>nor those you call my partie! But it is of the partie, that was sent unto</hi> Norwich <hi>for the peace of the Church, and betraied it: He told me, that</hi> I <hi>did lie, and all those that did say it.</hi> I <hi>replied to him, if the thing be proved, who then will be the Liar? and upon that we separated. This is a true nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the things that passed, to the best of my Memory, and</hi> I <hi>do believe, that</hi> Mr. Cisner <hi>cannot say the Contrarie, if he will speak the truth.</hi> Sirs, I <hi>do desire you to Judge, who gave the first offence, for he said that it was</hi> I, <hi>and my partie;</hi> Sirs I <hi>would know of him, or of the Companie, how</hi> I <hi>could have an hand, or had any thought to have made this difference, upon the Sermon of</hi> Mr. Delmey <hi>concerning Repentance.</hi> I <hi>say, if</hi> I <hi>would have done it, it was not in my power to have done it; for the difference was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween</hi> Mr. Delmey <hi>and the</hi> Consistory; <hi>so that</hi> I <hi>could not have an hand in it, because that</hi> I <hi>am not of the</hi> Consistory, <hi>and for that</hi> I <hi>answered unto</hi> Mr. Cisner, <hi>that it was of the partie, that were sent unto</hi> Norwich <hi>for the peace of the Church, but betraied it;
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:153451:24"/>There were Five Gentlemen in the</hi> Company; <hi>but.</hi> Mr, Cisner <hi>took it onelie to himself, when it was spoken of the</hi> Company. <hi>Which shewed plainly to me, that</hi> Mr. Cisner<hi>'s Conscience reproved him, or otherwise he would not have taken it unto himself. If he had asked me of whom</hi> I <hi>did speak it,</hi> I <hi>would have told him, that it was himself onely, and not any of the others; because</hi> I <hi>am assured, that all of them did their duties according to their Deputations, and onely</hi> Mr. Cisner <hi>did deal with</hi> Mr. D'asigny, <hi>against whom he was sent: And to do that, without the advice, and approbation of his brethren, (the Rest of the deputies,) and after that,</hi> Mr. Cisner <hi>had private Communication with</hi> Mr. D'asigny, <hi>and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared it not to the rest of the Deputies! If there was nothing else, but that against</hi> Mr. Cisner, <hi>it were enough to make him to be suspect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the thing is true: But it is declared sully by</hi> Mr. John Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neau, <hi>that he did give Counsell to</hi> Mr. D'asigny <hi>not to submit to the sentence, for that they had no power to constrain them. If that be not to betray, then</hi> I <hi>think there can be no treachery? And by his own Letter he acknowledgeth to have held the part of</hi> Mr. D'a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signy; <hi>which is against his deputation: And his own Testimony is more worthy to add faith unto, then all the Witnesses, that can be brought to the contrary.</hi> I <hi>will not insist any longer upon the particularities of it, because that</hi> I <hi>do here present unto you some Observations, that</hi> I <hi>have made upon both the abovesaid: and</hi> I <hi>doubt not, but it will be manifestly proved, that</hi> I <hi>have not invent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this accusation; But it is the good Providence of God, that hath brought these things so farr, and so to discover those things, that have been so long hid: for</hi> I <hi>say,</hi> I <hi>had no intention to have declared it: But he laid upon me such a false thing so that</hi> I <hi>could not contain my self, but spake, that which I have heard; for it came forth without my thinking of it.</hi> Sirs, <hi>I do desire you well to consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the sentence of the</hi> Colloquie, <hi>that is against</hi> Mr. D'asigny, <hi>and also the Commission given to the Deputies, to put the sentence in execution; and then consider the Testimony of</hi> Mr. Doneau, <hi>and principally</hi> Mr. Cisner's <hi>own Letter, and well weigh and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate them in the fear of God, and then Judge of them, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:153451:25"/>as the things do appear, &amp; that every one may bear his own bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and he that hath done amisse, acknowledge his fault: And in so doing, God will be glorified, and by that means the peace of the Church will be setled; for which I pray; and desire, that peace, and Truth may imbrace each other.</hi> Sirs, <hi>I am yet waiting for satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with impatience, touching the saying of</hi> Mr. Cisner, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that which he said to me of the Law.</hi> I <hi>say,</hi> I <hi>do hold him to be a Blasphemer, or an Atheist, untill he doth prove his saying, or explain it; or that he doth acknowledge his fault to God by true Repentance, for his evill speaking of God, and his Law; It seems to me, that it ought not to be so long time delayed in wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for it.</hi> I <hi>remain.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your affectionate servant, who<lb/> desires to maintain the Truth.<lb/> John Jurin <hi>Senior.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The reason why, I did not make any mention in the above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said Letter of their unjust proceedings, was, because that I would not incense them, hoping that they would have considered it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and so to have done justly.</p>
            <p>Here followe the Observations, that I delivered, and were read before the <hi>Company.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="documents">
                        <opener>
                           <salute>SIRS.</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                           <hi>TO build well upon any thing, is to lay a sure foundation. The ground of this dispute, that is befallen between</hi> me, <hi>and</hi> Mr. Cisner, <hi>is upon the matter of the</hi> Colloquie, <hi>held in</hi> London <hi>in</hi> August, 1646. <hi>in the</hi> Article. 87: <hi>where it is said, that</hi> Mr. D'a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signy <hi>is unworthy of the Ministery in the Church of</hi> Norwich, <hi>and besides he is interdicted the execution of it, not onely in the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> Norwich, <hi>but also in all the others, that are, or that may be
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:153451:25"/>of the</hi> Colloquie; <hi>who expresly defended them from admitting the said</hi> D'asigny <hi>in the execution of the Function of the Holy Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery:</hi> Mr. Cisner <hi>and the</hi> Deputies, <hi>that were sent unto</hi> Norwich <hi>to put in execution this</hi> sentence, <hi>undertook to do their duties therein; And I am fully satisfied, that all the Deputies did their duties, except onely</hi> Mr. Cisner, <hi>who did the contrary, as by the Testimony of</hi> Mr. John Doneau; <hi>and also as it doth appear by</hi> Mr. Cisner<hi>'s own Letter, which sheweth plainly, that he did not his dutie, as he had undertaken to do, but betraied the Cause, which he was sent to maintain; As it will be manifest by the</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servations <hi>following.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <div type="observations">
                           <head>Observations on the Testimony of Mr. <hi>John Doneau</hi> Juuin<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>, against Mr. <hi>Cisner.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p n="1">1. <hi>Assoon as the</hi> Deputies <hi>were arrived in</hi> Norwich, <hi>Mr.</hi> D'a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signy, <hi>and</hi> Mr. Doneau <hi>went to their Lodging, and then sent for</hi> Mr Cisner, <hi>and he came to them into the Chamber next to theirs: And having saluted</hi> M. Cisner, <hi>said unto him,</hi> you must declare to us all the grounds of your business, without concealing any thing. <hi>This shews clearly, that</hi> Mr. D'asigny, <hi>and</hi> Cisner <hi>kept Correspondency together, seeing that</hi> Mr. D'asigny <hi>spake so freely to</hi> Mr. Cisner; <hi>and it also shews the Testimony of</hi> Mr. Doneau <hi>to be true.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="2">2. <hi>Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>answered,</hi> that he could not tarry, for two Reasons: First, because that he feared he should be suspected; Secondly, that they were then upon the business, for the which they were deputed; but he promised them to meet them on the morrow morning, at an house in a place, called <hi>Sandling</hi>'s behind the great Church by the River, being a place out of the way, for fear that he should be discovered. <hi>If Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>in so doing, had done nothing but his duty, he had no need to fear his
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:153451:26"/>being discovered: But his Conscience reproved him, and this shews, that this his dealing was not lawfull, but contrary to, and against his Deputation.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="3">3. <hi>That Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>left Mr.</hi> D'asigny, <hi>and Mr</hi> Doneau <hi>in the next Chamber, joyning to theirs, where they did hear, and understand all that they debated; and neverthelesse Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>did not give any notice of it to the</hi> Company. <hi>This was to betray the</hi> Company, <hi>and their affairs.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="4">4. <hi>Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>according to his promise met them at the above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said place, between seven and eight of the clock in the morning, and continued with them till above Twelve at noone; and disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to Mr.</hi> D'asigny, <hi>and Mr.</hi> Doneau <hi>all the Resolutions of the Deputies and counselled Mr.</hi> D'asigny, <hi>and Mr.</hi> Doneau <hi>not to submit for they had no power to constrain them to do it. If this be not betraying, there can be none in Church affairs? But it appears that he hath betrayed, for these three Reasons.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <list>
                              <item>1. <hi>First, because he had no Commission to treat with them by himself, (I say,) with Mr.</hi> D'asigny, <hi>who was under the Censure, and sentence of the</hi> Colloquie.</item>
                              <item>2. <hi>Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>was sent with the other Deputies; And so he ought not to have treated without their Advice, and approbation; neverthelesse he hath discovered all their businesse to those, against whom they were deputed.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>3. <hi>He counsell's them not to submit, for they had no power to constrain them. Is not this to betray, by giving such Counsell to Mr.</hi> D'asigny? <hi>seeing that Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>had undertaken to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:153451:26"/>pursue the sentence of the</hi> Colloquie; <hi>yet neverthelesse he coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selled them not to submit: And whither this is not to betray, I think no man will question.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                           <p n="5">5. <hi>We may observe the great Providence of God in discovering that, which hath been kept so long secret; Considering what Mr.</hi> Doneau, <hi>saith,</hi> Although the abovesaid be very true, I had no intention to declare it, nor have been required, but understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the affront, that Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> did to Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> openly in the Church, I could not refrain my self to declare this, which I had resolved to bury for ever. <hi>God is just, and doth disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in his good time the wickednesse of persons, and their unjust Actions.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="observations">
                           <head>Observations on the Letter of Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> which he did write to obtain Testimony to justifie himself.</head>
                           <p n="1">1. <hi>The first Observation is, that he wrote to Mr.</hi> D'asigny, <hi>who was under the</hi> Sentence <hi>of the</hi> Colloquie, <hi>which judged him unworthy of the Holy Ministery in all the Churches of the</hi> Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie: <hi>Also he wrote to the</hi> Elders, <hi>and</hi> Deacons, <hi>that were in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice with</hi> D'asigny, <hi>when the</hi> Deputies <hi>were at</hi> Norwich, <hi>to put in execution the</hi> sentence <hi>of the</hi> Colloquie <hi>against Mr.</hi> D'asigny. <hi>Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>also wrote to them to obtain a</hi> Testimony <hi>from them to justifie him against the accusation. If Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>would have justified himself to have done his duty, according to his deputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he ought to have written to Mr.</hi> De Laune, <hi>and his partie, in favour of whom he was sent. He hath received Testimony from</hi> D'asigny, <hi>and his partie, against whom he was sent. Which shew's evidently that he hath held with the partie of Mr.</hi> D'asigny <hi>against his deputation; and so it proves the Testimony of Mr.</hi> Doneau <hi>to be very true.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="2">
                              <pb n="44" facs="tcp:153451:27"/> 2. <hi>He flatter's those</hi> Gentlemen <hi>to obtain a Testimony from them, and blame's the</hi> Consistory <hi>of</hi> London, <hi>saying,</hi> I must avow that your <hi>Consistory</hi> hath had some Cause to be discontented for an Apparent reproach, that was done to it. <hi>It is to be considered, if Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>did not dictate the Letter, and neverthelesse laye's the blame on the</hi> Consistory. <hi>Is not that Hypocrisie?</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="3">3. <hi>He doth incourage them not to contribute more, than the summe that they do allow for his entertainment,</hi> in doing all you can possible: <hi>for as the high Dutch Proverb saith,</hi> Where there is nothing, the Emperour himself looseth his Right. <hi>If we should do the same to Mr.</hi> Cisner, <hi>It would not be well pleasing to him; but would be the just Law of Retaliation, to do to him, as he doth counsell those</hi> Gentlemen <hi>against Mr.</hi> De Laune, <hi>their ancient Pastor.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="4">4. <hi>Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>doth acknowledge, that the sentence was against their</hi> Consistory, <hi>and Mr.</hi> D'asigny, <hi>their Pastor.</hi> Now ye all know, how holily and justly I have carried my self in that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, having not sought any thing, but the good, and peace, and edification of your Church. <hi>This doth Confirm the Testimony of Mr.</hi> Doneau; <hi>And the Testimony of Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst himself is more Authentique, than all the Testimonies, or witnesses, that might be brought to the contrary. So that there is Two witnesses to prove the Accusation, viz. Of Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>against himself, and that of Mr.</hi> Doneau <hi>proves clearly, that Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>hath betrayed the Church of Mr.</hi> De Laune, <hi>in maintaining Mr.</hi> D'asigny <hi>contrary to his depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="5">5. <hi>He calls the Colloquie</hi> Instruments of violence, <hi>and scoff's at the</hi> presumption of those, who under a pretence to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern the Churches, and to settle good order, do indeavour to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:153451:27"/>bring in a Tyrannicall dominion over the Inheritance of the Lord. <hi>Is not this the greatest defamation (that can be,) of the</hi> Colloquie? <hi>and thereby shewes his hypocrisie, perfidiousnesse, and unfaithfulnesse; having undertaken the Commission of the</hi> Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie <hi>with the other</hi> Deputies, <hi>and neverthelesse speakes so wickedly of them. Then it is no marvell that he hath so betraied them, seeing that he speakes so unworthily of them!</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="6">6. <hi>He speakes unworthily of Mr.</hi> Delmey, <hi>who is with God: When as the Divel, and</hi> Michael (<hi>the</hi> Archangel) <hi>disputed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the bodie of</hi> Moses, <hi>the Angel himself durst not bring any railing accusation; but Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>dares speak unworthilie of the faithfull servant of God deceased. Which shewe's the hatred, and rancor that is in the heart of Mr.</hi> Cisner. <hi>It would be well to be satisfied by Mr.</hi> Cisner, <hi>if such expressions, (Calumnia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory,) be a mark of a true Minister of</hi> Jesus Christ!</p>
                           <p n="7">7. <hi>He speakes unworthilie of his Fellow-Minister Mr.</hi> Delmey (Inheritor of the violent passions of his father,) that Satan hath raised me a great persecution by that means. <hi>The Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture called it persecution, when one is persecuted for maintaining the Truth: but it hath not been heard, that there hath been any debate for anie Truth: but if one be prosecuted for unfaithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, It is a just Reward of his merit, as this is on Mr.</hi> Cisner, <hi>for betraying the Cause, which he undertook to maintain. And</hi> Sirs, <hi>you may very well remember, what imprecations Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>made before you in the</hi> Consistory <hi>touching this businesse!</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="8">8. <hi>He saith of me, and Mr. Fervacques,</hi> (who not content to persecute me by back-biting, &amp;c.) <hi>Whereto, The observation of the Precedent Section may serve for the answering thereof. But for his venomous, and aspersing tongue, Its hoped, that the</hi> Consistory <hi>will do justice, seeing the Thing is so clearly proved,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:153451:28"/>by Mr.</hi> Doneau, <hi>and also by his own Letter: By which it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears plainly, and manifestly, that he hath taken Mr.</hi> D'asigny<hi>'s part, directly against his deputation; which justifie's us that we have not invented it, and are not Tellers of lies, nor</hi> Chiquaneurs, <hi>as Mr</hi> Cisner <hi>termed us before the</hi> Consistory. <hi>And therefore he ought to prove his saying, or acknowledge his fault.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="9">9. <hi>He saith,</hi> seeing that your <hi>Consistory,</hi> (then upon the which Mr. <hi>D'asigny</hi> was President,) was the onely Church of <hi>Norwich;</hi> from which Mr. <hi>De Laune</hi> separated, and was followed by some few persons, who might not nor ought to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to him the name, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Gentlemen, <hi>I desire you will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider well and deliberately this Particular, comparing it with the sentence of the</hi> Colloquie, <hi>which condemne's Mr.</hi> D'asigny, <hi>and judgeth him unworthy of the holy Ministery in the Churches of the</hi> Colloquie; <hi>the said</hi> Colloquie <hi>justifying Mr.</hi> De Laune. <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthelesse Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>condemne's Mr.</hi> De Laune, <hi>and saies,</hi> (followed with some who might not and ought not to attribute the name: <hi>Is not this to condemn Mr.</hi> De Laune, <hi>and his partie, and justifie Mr.</hi> D'asigny, <hi>and his partie, quite contrary to his Commission and Judgement of the</hi> Colloquie? <hi>So that it doth ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie the Testimony of Mr.</hi> Doneau; <hi>And Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>by his own Letter maintains to have betrayed Mr.</hi> De Laune, <hi>and his</hi> Church, <hi>which was acknowledged the Church of</hi> Norwich <hi>by the</hi> Colloquie: <hi>And therein he hath betrayed the</hi> Colloquie, <hi>which represents all our Churches; but especially our Church of</hi> London, <hi>who have been at so great Charges for that journey: which in all justice, and equity Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>ought to repay.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="10">10. <hi>He saith,</hi> how could I have betrayed the Church, of the which, (according to my Accusers,) I was in the same the Patron, friend, and Advocate. <hi>In this he doth say very true, and</hi> I <hi>beleeve it. He saith, that I and Mr.</hi> Fervacques <hi>have said it, when
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:153451:28"/>as we have not said it, nor ever thought to have done so; but his own Conscience say's it, and testfie's it, that he is the patron, friend and Advocate; and so he goes on vaunting, and discovering himself, what he is; and without doubt, he thought, that this Letter should never have been discovered, and come to light: But by the good providence of God it is come to Light, whom it hath pleased, that it should be made manifest to the world for a lively Testimony against him.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="11">11 <hi>He saie's,</hi> truely as I know not any secret, which hath been committed to me by any <hi>Company,</hi> or by any particular person that may be, so I could not reveal any secret. <hi>Any man may easily judge of the falsenesse of his saying, who hath never so little Judgement, or reason, seeing that he makes no more Conscience in writing. Whereby it may be concluded, that he had the same Conscience to betray the Church, and the Cause, which he had undertaken to have maintained, according to his deputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and may aswell justifie himself not to have betrayed his Trust, as he doth justifie himself, that he knows no secrets committed to him.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="12">12. <hi>He promised, that</hi> Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> and himself would do in manner, that the sentence should be suspended, and that their Cause against Mr. <hi>De Laune</hi> should be read over again, and examined, and that all justice should be done them, without having regard to the appearance of any body. <hi>If he had any such Commission, he would do well to produce it, to make his saying appear to be true. But in so doing he doth in effect condemn the very</hi> Colloquie, <hi>not to have judged justly.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="13">13. <hi>He is afraid,</hi> that his Innocency may not be made sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected by some false Testimony. <hi>The Truth is, he is afraid, that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:153451:29"/>the truth should be known. But God hath been pleased, that the truth should be manifested clearly, and that by Mr.</hi> Cisner<hi>'s own Letter. So that it is evident that Mr</hi> Doneau<hi>'s Testimony is also very true, that Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>hath upheld Mr.</hi> D'asigny, <hi>against his deputation, from the</hi> Colloquie. <hi>And in that which Mr.</hi> Cis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>thought to have saved himself, he is so firmly, and positively taken, that he cannot find out a way to escape. God is just, and will give to every one, accordingly as they have done.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>I desire the Reader to take notice of the later part of my Letter, preceeding my aforesaid Observations, <hi>How I charge</hi> Mr. Cisner, <hi>for that he hath spoken against the Law, and do hold him to be a Blasphemer, or an Atheist, untill he doth prove his Saying, or acknowledge his fault to God, by true Repentance;</hi> And neverthelesse I could not receive from the <hi>Consistory,</hi> or Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> any answer to this day, either to prove it by the word of God, or to deny it.</p>
            <p>Now after all the aforesaid severall Observations, made by me, were read in the <hi>Consistory,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> made a Reply thereunto, but with so many falsities, and impudent untruths, that they were in no wise beseeming the profession of one, that pretends to know, that there is a <hi>God,</hi> and that he is just, and will give to every one, according to his works: And in truth were such, as that neither my self, nor Mr. <hi>Fervacques</hi> could with patience hear him, and forbear to refute, and convince him. <hi>But the</hi> Company <hi>desired us to be patient, till they had done; And then we should say, what we pleased.</hi> Upon which their promise we rested satisfied, till Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> had concluded. And then we desired to reply to his falsities. But Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> said in a deriding manner, <hi>It could not be done, before that he had asked the Companies Advise.</hi> Which I said was his duty to do; And upon his request we with-drew, waiting for the Companies result.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:153451:29"/>
            <p> A while after we were called before the <hi>Company,</hi> who said, <hi>that they had considered of the matter; But did not find</hi> Mr. Cisner <hi>Guilty of that, wherewith we had charged him. However for the peace of the Church, all things passed should be buried under foot, and forgotten: desiring us to go to</hi> Mr. Cisner, <hi>and reconcile our selves to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is fit I should give you some accompt, who at this present, (when this sentence was passed,) were Members of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> Because very ordinarily every six moneths some of the Elders go out, and others come in. Wherefore the <hi>Pastors</hi> were Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> Mr. <hi>Stouppe,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Cisner.</hi> The Elders were Mr. <hi>Florantine Tainturier,</hi> Mr. <hi>Samuel Vincent,</hi> Mr. <hi>James Ʋancourt,</hi> Mr. <hi>Isaac De Lillers,</hi> Mr. <hi>Isaac Vanney,</hi> Mr. <hi>David Bouquet,</hi> Mr. <hi>Peter La Roche,</hi> Mr. <hi>James De Quen,</hi> Mr. <hi>Deriek <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> M<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Peter Rouseau,</hi> Mr. <hi>Peter Bar,</hi> Mr. <hi>Paul D'obey,</hi> &amp; Mr. <hi>Peter Caulier.</hi> Which three last mentioned persons, being (as well may be supposed) deluded and seduced by Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> and Mr. <hi>Stouppe,</hi> have been with them the grand disturbers of our Churches peace, and the Conductors in, and Fomentors of all the troubles, that have befallen it, as I do probably conjecture. And yet Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> hath had the Confidence to retort upon us, <hi>That it was we that had betraied the Church:</hi> Which scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Aspersions the <hi>Consistory</hi> would never, (though often intreated by us,) order him to prove against us; or give us any satisfaction for, or vindication against it. For which grand Injustice, and partiality there is none I hope, but of merit, and desert not will condemn and reprove them.</p>
            <p>Thus having discovered the persons and their unjust Actions, I shall proceed to give you a further Accompt of my self and Mr. <hi>Fervacques:</hi> Who, assoon as we heard Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the said unheard of and unjust sentence, <hi>Did instantly protest against the same as unequall, and appealled from it, and them to the next</hi> Colloquie, <hi>to whom: we would submit and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:153451:30"/>the Company to take notice of our Appeal, and enter it in their Books; For that they had dealt with us falsely, deceitfully, and wickedly: For having justified Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>in all his wickednesses, they thereby had made his sins their own, for which they must one day give an Accompt. And upon this we desired them, since our divisions were so great, to he pleased to call a</hi> Colloquie <hi>for the appeasing, and reconciling thereof.</hi> They said they would consider of it, and give us Answer in due time. But hearing nothing from them Mr. <hi>Fervacques</hi> and my self went to our <hi>Elder</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siring him to propound it in the <hi>Consistory, that a</hi> Colloquie <hi>might be called.</hi> He did so, and returned us their Answer, <hi>That Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>being out of town and-till he returned they could give us no answer.</hi> Shewing plainly, that they cannot do any thing without him. I thereupon replied to our Elder, <hi>that they ought to do it; without</hi> Mr. Cisner <hi>for if he and his friends could hinder it, We should not have a</hi> Colloquie <hi>in their daies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At Mr. <hi>Cisner's</hi> return, We went to the <hi>Consistory,</hi> and after long attendance were called in: <hi>We told</hi> them, <hi>we came to know their Resolutions for the calling the Colloquie.</hi> They desired us to with-draw, and we should have their Answer; But instead thereof, they at the last did arise in a Confusion. Wherefore seeing them come out one after another, and one of them cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, he would come no more amongst them, I said to <hi>Mr.</hi> D'obey, <hi>What? Have you, made us stay thus long, and now give us no Answer!</hi> He returned, <hi>that we should have it at the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change.</hi> To which I said, <hi>that if that were their answer, we would come to them, when they were in better order.</hi> And then he told me, <hi>that</hi> Mr, Delmey <hi>would give us the Answer.</hi> Who coming out said, <hi>that the Companies Resolution was to stay the ordinary time of the</hi> Colloquie.</p>
            <p>A moneth, or two after my Appeal made as aforesaid, my Elder brought me my Token for the Sacrament of the Lords Supper: But for that we somuch pressed the <hi>Companie</hi> for a <hi>Colloquie,</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:153451:30"/>they seemed to be angry, and that to be revenged on us, they would keep us from the Sacrament. And the second or third month after my Elder said to me, <hi>that he had order to keep back my token, till</hi> I <hi>did reconcile my self to Mr.</hi> Cisner. <hi>I asked him If I had committed any thing since my Appeal, that made me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy. For that having made an Appeal, all things ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, as they were, till they we<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e decided in</hi> Colloquie. <hi>And being I was not kept from the Sacrament before my Appeal made, nea, not the first or second moneth after it,</hi> I <hi>therefore ought not at all to be debarred from it, especially not having committed anie fact after my said Appeal, which did anie waies render me unworthy or disabled.</hi> And this is according to the Act of our eighth <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie,</hi> in the year 1589. in the words ensuing, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="document">
                        <head>Article, the 8<seg rend="sup">th</seg>.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>No appeal shall be received, before that the sentence be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by the</hi> Consistory: <hi>Which in Case of an Appeal, shall stand intirely untill it be fully decided by the</hi> Colloquie. <hi>Ʋnlesse that the Delinquent shall desist from his Appeal, and satisfieth the</hi> Consistory.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>After this on a Lords day in the evening Mr. <hi>Stouppe,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bar,</hi> and Mr. <hi>La Roche</hi> came to my house to persuade me to reconcile my self to Mr. <hi>Cisner.</hi> I took it as a Complement from them, and said, <hi>I was ready to do it, when he had given me satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, and not before.</hi> Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> replyed <hi>that</hi> I <hi>ought to do it, and that by dispute he would convince anie man that</hi> I <hi>ought so to do.</hi> To which I said, <hi>that</hi> I <hi>accepted of a Dispute:</hi> But he made me no answer. I therefore further objected, <hi>that if he was a man of his word, he would be as good as his word?</hi> Whereto he answered, <hi>that he could not undertake it without the consent of the</hi> Consistory. By which I perfectly discerned, that it was but a mere Osten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and Uaunting in Mr. <hi>Stouppe;</hi> naked words, without
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:153451:31"/>deeds; and in fine and Ayery, empty Complement, whereby to sound and fathom my Inclination; For ever since I have heard no more of it. At that time Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> acknowledged, <hi>that Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>had preached against the Law; And had compared it to a Diall, that marks</hi> Twelve, <hi>and stricke's</hi> six; <hi>saying,</hi> Is not that an Hypocrite? And also Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> said, that Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> compared <hi>the Law to a squint eyed man, seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to look one way, and indeed looke's another:</hi> Further saying, Is not that Hypocrisie?</p>
            <p>Our Divisions encreasing more and more, Mr. <hi>Fervacques</hi> and I did hold it our duties to use all lawfull means for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination thereof; And therefore presented our selves to the <hi>Consistory,</hi> for that they held not fit to call a <hi>Colloquie</hi> till the ordinary time, as is before mentioned, <hi>Desiring them in the mean time to call a</hi> Classis <hi>to prevent the further growth of our differences.</hi> They thereupon desired us to with-draw. And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward calling us in again said, <hi>that they found not such a word in the Discipline, as a</hi> Classis, <hi>and that it was an Innovation: And therefore they were resolved to stay the ordinary time for a</hi> Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie. Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> being asked by me, <hi>when that time would be, said about nine or ten moneths hence.</hi> I replyed to him, <hi>that</hi> I <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it was more, If they had not altered the time, For a</hi> Colloquie <hi>was to be every three years;</hi> But he affirmed, <hi>in every two years.</hi> However we wondred at their term of <hi>Innovation,</hi> in respect of a <hi>Classis.</hi> Saying, <hi>they could not be so ignorant in our govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, For that Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>knew full well, that himself had been at a Classis;</hi> But I perceived, they desired to defer the business, and not to come to the Touch-stone, as not willing to, or brooking a triall, and examination thereof.</p>
            <p>We further desired the <hi>Consistory</hi> to inform us, <hi>for what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, they did keep back our Tokens.</hi> They said, <hi>Because we would not reconcile to Mr.</hi> Cisner. We answered, <hi>that they well knew, that some time past we offered to do it upon good and just grounds;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:153451:31"/>referring it to themselves to propound them which; they had never yet done: But that now having made our Appeal to the</hi> Colloquie, <hi>all proceedings for that businesse ought to rest as it was, when we appealed, till it was ended by the</hi> Colloquie. <hi>For that, to proceed after an Appeal made, was to usurpe that power, which the</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory <hi>ought not. And so it was tyranny and oppression in them to proceed against any one for the same fact, for which he had appeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, And they could not with hold our Tokens, unlesse we had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted something since our Appeal, which made us unworthy: Which we demanded of them to prove and make to appear: Or else they had no ground for their Actions: Which we verily beleeved they had not: Thereby</hi> fully discovering their Iniquity and injustice in not discharging the duties of their Elder-ships, having admitted Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> notwithstanding his wickedness, and that he hath not a<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> given satisfaction for his Atheisticall, and erroneous Doctrine, and treacherous dealings so apparently detected, and proved against him: And because they justified him, and held communion with him, protecting him from due triall, and Censure, we thereupon with-drew.</p>
            <p>Considering the premisses, And that we had so fully proved the Accusation against Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> Mr. <hi>Fervacques,</hi> and I being as aforesaid in the <hi>Consistory,</hi> demanded <hi>of them, that satisfastion should be given us by Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>for his slandering of us before them, which they might well remember, since with such Imprecations he had called God, and the holy Ghost to witnesse, that the Accusation was false, and that we had invented it, And were iuventors of Lies, and Reporters of Lies, and</hi> Chiquaneurs <hi>and also for his slandering and scandalizing us in his Letter to the Gentlemen at</hi> Norwich. We therefore desired the <hi>Company</hi> to do us justice, either that Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> might prove his saying, or acknowledge his fault; Who answered, <hi>that if we would reconcile our selves to Mr.</hi> Cisner, <hi>they would then do that, which was reason.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Members of the Church at length perceiving the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence of the business, with much Importunity pressed the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:153451:32"/>Elders to call a <hi>Colloquie:</hi> Who finding themselves thus solli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited, gave out to the people, <hi>that if we would defray the Charges of the Deputies of the Churches, We then should have a</hi> Colloquie. Which Report being made to me, I went to my Elder and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired to know, <hi>if it were true;</hi> who said, <hi>it was so:</hi> I asked, <hi>if there was no hinderance, but want of money;</hi> he replied, <hi>there was not; And that if I would undertake to pay the Charges, we should have one speedilie.</hi> I desired him to propound to the <hi>Company, that I would undertake to pay the Charges, so as the</hi> Colloquie <hi>might be called suddainlie before the winter.</hi> Which proposition he made: But the <hi>Company</hi> found out evasions still to put off the <hi>Colloquie.</hi> And therefore I wrote to them in <hi>French,</hi> the translation whereof followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>To the Pastors, and Elders, and Deacons assembled in <hi>Consistory</hi> London.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIRS!</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HAving understood that some</hi> Elders <hi>have given it out,</hi> that if we would pay the Charges of the other Churches De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties, we should have a Colloquie; <hi>This made me to addresse my self to Mr.</hi> Tainturier <hi>to demaund of him,</hi> If there was any such thing. <hi>He told me,</hi> that there was such a proposition made. <hi>I told him,</hi> if there was no hinderance, but the want of money. I would undertake to furnish it, if they would call a <hi>Colloquie</hi> suddenly before it was Winter. I told him that I had yet so so much affection for the peace of the Church, that I would inlarge my self for the good of it. I <hi>told him,</hi> that our Church hath had Charity towards other Churches, when they were in division, as <hi>Norwich,</hi> and <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and hath not the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory Charity for it self? The Charity unto the other Churches hath it taken away that, which we ought to have unto our own? <hi>The Proverb is,</hi> that Charity begins at home. Sirs, <hi>the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:153451:32"/>answer that you were pleased to send to me, was,</hi> when the two Churches, that have no Pastors are provided, then you would write to the Church, that is to call it, desiring them to call a Colloquie. Sirs, <hi>Seeing that you have changed your Resolutions, and found out another delay to put off the Calling of the</hi> Colloquie <hi>so suddainly, as was propounded, in putting it of untill the Two Churches that have no Pastors be furnished with Pastors, which cannot be done so suddainlie: If that had been told me before, I would not have offered you that expedient. Seeing that you do not keep to your proposition, I am discharged of mine. If I did yeild unto your last proposition, the world would judge me to be prodigall. Considering your former sayings, that the</hi> Colloquie <hi>ought to be seven or eight moneths hence by course; the Two Churches being not now furnished, and caunot besuddenly, for if they were now upon the place, it would be some time before they could be setled, and then it would be the depth of Winter; &amp; then you will judge the sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son not fit for them to come.</hi> Sirs, <hi>Me thinks! At present there is as manie Churches, as in former times, and there might be a</hi> Colloquie <hi>if you would.</hi> Sirs, <hi>I do not know why Mr.</hi> Stouppe <hi>speaks so un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthilie of Mr.</hi> Danois <hi>and Mr.</hi> Payen, <hi>saying,</hi> who are they? <hi>This is to despise them: for what reason he doth, it is known unto himself, But I say, that it is not seemly, that such a young man should be so haughtie to despise others.</hi> Sirs, <hi>I fear if Mr.</hi> Stouppe, <hi>and some others (if they can hinder it,) we shall have no</hi> Colloquie: <hi>for one may say the like of the Two Churches, that have no Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors; for in all likelihood, they will be furnished with young Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, that have not yet exercised the Ministery, and so will not have anie great experience in the government of the Churches: And so it might be said we cannot have</hi> Colloquies! Sirs, <hi>I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that I have left you without anie just excuse; For without doubt if your Cause were good, and just, you would desire to come to a suddain end; for I have offered unto you all the wayes to a</hi> Colloquie; <hi>or to some Ministers of our</hi> Colloquie, <hi>or to a</hi> Classis, <hi>or to the Gentlemen of the</hi> Dutch, <hi>or to</hi> English <hi>Ministers, or to anie persons, that are not interressed. My cause is good and just,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:153451:33"/>and I do not fear to make it appear before all the world.</hi> (Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men <hi>the</hi> Deacons,) <hi>I do not know, why the</hi> Elders <hi>have stayed so long time, before they have called you to have your Advise, and counsell!</hi> Sirs, <hi>seeing now that they have called you to their Assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, all that I do desire of you is, before that you do imbrace the one, or the other partie, I desire you to read the sentence of the</hi> Colloquie <hi>against Mr</hi> D'asigny. Secondly, <hi>I desire you to read the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission and order given to the</hi> Gentlemen, <hi>the Deputies to put the sentence in execution.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>I desire you to read the Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of Mr.</hi> John Doneau <hi>against Mr.</hi> Cisner. Fourthly, <hi>I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire you to read Mr.</hi> Cisner<hi>'s own Letter, and consider it verie well. Then you will have some knowledge of those things; Then you may judge, if Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>hath done his dutie, according to his deputation, and Commission, accordingly as he had undertaken it to do.</hi> Sirs, <hi>there is another proposition that I do propose unto both Companies,</hi> that is; <hi>Mr.</hi> D'obey, <hi>and Mr.</hi> Bar <hi>being <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Mr.</hi> D'esmare<hi>'s, (speaking of the differences,) and especially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Mr.</hi> Cisner<hi>'s Letter) in the end Mr.</hi> D'obey <hi>said, that we had a Letter from</hi> Norwich, <hi>that they would not submit to the</hi> Colloquie <hi>before the Deputies went to</hi> Norwich. Sirs, <hi>there was no bodie at Mr.</hi> D'esmare<hi>'s, but Mr.</hi> D'obey, <hi>and Mr.</hi> Bar, <hi>and Mr.</hi> D'obey <hi>said, we had a Letter. So it appeared by that word</hi> (we) <hi>he comprehended Mr.</hi> Bar <hi>also; So</hi> Sirs <hi>you see that Mr.</hi> D'obey <hi>and others have kept Correspondence with Mr.</hi> D'a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signy <hi>against the</hi> Colloquie, <hi>and 'tis apparent that some other Brothren have had a hand in that businesse. So by the sayings of Mr.</hi> D'obey, <hi>I prove the Testimonie of Mr.</hi> Doneau <hi>to be true, touching the Correspondence with Mr.</hi> D'asigny; <hi>for Mr.</hi> D'obey <hi>doe's acknowledge it. Seeing this is so, then it is no marvell, that the things have been carried so, with such unjustice in the</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory, <hi>seeing that there is of the</hi> Company <hi>that is guiltie of Mr.</hi> Cisner<hi>'s fault, and are</hi> Judges, <hi>and</hi> parties <hi>in their own</hi> Cause. Sirs, <hi>I do not impute this unto all the</hi> Elders, <hi>but onelie unto those that are guiltie. This word</hi> (we) <hi>is of a large extent! then it is no marvell, that those that are guiltie with good and fair words have
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:153451:33"/>carryed away some other Brethren by their Subtilties to be of their Judgement, to justifie the guilty.</hi> Sirs, <hi>I doe desire you to take this business into serious consideration, and very well to examine it, that you be no longer deceived by fair words; for God has begun to disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and I doubt not but he will go on to discover more &amp; more, and truth will overcome falshood: Falsehood is but a poor refuge: And I am assured, that in the day of Judgement it will not be to them an hiding place.</hi> Sirs, <hi>I have another thing against Mr.</hi> Bar, <hi>which he said at Mr.</hi> D'esmare<hi>'s: Mr.</hi> D'esmare <hi>said, they had justified Mr.</hi> Cisner, <hi>before that they had heard us: Mr.</hi> Bar <hi>said, that was false. I do maintain, that this is true: for those</hi> Gentlemen <hi>that were then in the</hi> Consistory <hi>cannot denie it, if they please but to remember, when we presented our selves with the Testimonie of Mr.</hi> Doneau, <hi>and Mr.</hi> Cisner<hi>'s Letter, the</hi> Company <hi>would not permit them to be read in the Audience of the</hi> Company, <hi>and seeing no other Remedie, in part we yeilded; upon Condition, that they would hear us what we had to say, before that they did come to a sentence: The which they promised us, that we should be heard of all, that we had to say. I say, though you reiterated this promise to us, yet neverthelesse you proceeded to the sentence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that you had heard us speak one word, and you justified</hi> Mr. Cisner, <hi>and that he was not guiltie in anie thing; and you desired</hi> Mr. Delmey, <hi>having some power on us for to come to us to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suade us to reconcile our selves to Mr.</hi> Cisner. Sirs, <hi>you know that this is true, and I am persuaded, that those that were then in</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory <hi>cannot say to the contrarie; for I am persuaded, that the most part of you will not denie the truth.</hi> Sirs, <hi>I do desire to judge, if</hi> Mr. Bar <hi>hath done the dutie of an</hi> Elder <hi>in going about to sow falsities against me.</hi> Sirs, <hi>Considering the false Reports that are dispersed by some of you, Consider if that does not incite me to justifie my self, by putting out a Narration in publick of what hath passed in these differences, that it might be known to the world the wrong, and injustice, that you have done to me.</hi> Sirs, <hi>I confesse I am enough inclined to do it, but also I should be verie sorrie to bring dishonour upon the whole Church, for the fault of some few
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:153451:34"/>particular persons; and I see that the divisions increase more and more. Therefore, I say, it is more then time that ye should think of some way of peace, and those have been offered unto you, and the guiltie will not imbrace them, but will have their wills, and that rather the Church should break for once, for a good blow. What good blowe that may be, my simple judgement cannot apprehend! but I say, that they that do delight in troubles, and Contentions, if one should wish them their fill of them, in the end they would find, that they have had too much of it, for their good &amp; Contentment.</hi> Sirs, <hi>It was my desire at the first to be discharged of this businesse, and trouble, and that I am of the same minde; and that hath made me to propound so manie waies to come to a just peace.</hi> Sirs, <hi>Seeing that it is not resolved to call a</hi> Colloquie, <hi>before the Two Churches (now vacant of Pastors) be furnished, and that cannot be done suddainlie: Therefore I once more offer unto you to prevent the evil that may befall, if you do stay the ordinarie time of the</hi> Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie: I <hi>saie,</hi> I <hi>do offer you to referre all the differences, that do concern me to the</hi> Gentlemen <hi>the</hi> Minister <hi>and</hi> Elders <hi>of the</hi> Dutch Church, <hi>to determine them, untill the</hi> Colloquie <hi>be as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled, to put a finall end. This is that which</hi> I <hi>have to represent to you for the present, and rest.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your affectionate servant,</hi> (I <hi>say</hi>)<lb/>
                        <hi>of them that desire truth and<lb/> peace.</hi> John Jurin <hi>Senior.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>London</hi>
                        <date>the 9<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>October,</hi> 1655.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Postscript.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIRS.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IT may be Mr.</hi> Bar <hi>will saie of this Letter, or Paper, as he said to me on</hi> Munday <hi>last of those formerlie presented to you,</hi> that they were fit to be sent unto Bedlam. <hi>Seeing it is a Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam that hath said it,</hi> I <hi>do bear with him.</hi> Sirs, <hi>seeing that there
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:153451:34"/>is no reason in them,</hi> I <hi>do desire to have your Consent, that I may make all things publick, seeing that they be onelie fit for Bedlam; It will be greatlie for your Advantage, and will make your Cause verie good! And if you please to condescend to it, then</hi> I <hi>do desire you, that you would be pleased to let me have the Letter, or the Copy of it in which</hi> I <hi>spake of the fire, which came so near our Church; for by mistake</hi> I <hi>have torn the Copie of it, and cannot find all the pieces thereof.</hi> I <hi>have importuned you verie of ten for it, and you have not granted me it: If you please to let me have a Copie of it, or the Letter it self, I do promise to restore it again to you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>per</hi> John Jurin <hi>Senior.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>To this Letter, which I am sure the <hi>Consistory</hi> had in their hands, I received no Answer.</p>
            <p>The differences still encreasing more and more, many par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Members of the Church pressed hard upon the <hi>Consistory</hi> to call a <hi>Colloquie</hi> to decide, and end all our differences: In so much that at the length they resolved to call one: And in <hi>December</hi> wrote their Letters to the Churches, <hi>Desiring them to send their Deputies to be here in</hi> London <hi>on the</hi> 10th <hi>day of Januarie,</hi> 1655. <hi>And that they would defray their Charges.</hi> But I desire the Reader to take notice, that it is not the ordinary practice to pay the charges of the other Churches; And I never heard, that it hath been done heretofore. But when as the <hi>Consistorie</hi> propounded it to me formerly, they did so, suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing that I would not have undertaken it: And made it a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfuge, and Reserve, whereby to have laid the fault upon us, Yet however Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> opposed it, saying, <hi>they must then do somewhat for us in recompence.</hi> Nevertheless being the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistorie</hi> themselves undertook it, we were very well satisfied; For I am fully assured, that the plurality of the Deputies were such godly and religious men, that they would not be tempted to do any unjust action. At which unseasonable time of the year
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:153451:35"/>the <hi>Churches</hi> at the <hi>Consistorie</hi>'s request sent their <hi>Deputies,</hi> excepting onely the Church of <hi>Norwich,</hi> whose <hi>Deputies</hi> came not at all. And all the rest being met together in <hi>London,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired to form, and constitute themselves into a <hi>Colloquie.</hi> But the <hi>Consistorie</hi> would not permit them, <hi>unlesse they would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise to joyn with the</hi> Dutch Colloquie, <hi>which was then sitting:</hi> Whereto the Deputies replied, <hi>that if after they were rightly formed, they found the businesse too heavie for them, and difficult, then they might joyn with the</hi> Dutch, <hi>if they saw it good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I would have the <hi>Reader</hi> understand the manner, and Custom of our <hi>Colloquies:</hi> Which is, That he who was <hi>Presi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> of the last preceding <hi>Colloquie,</hi> in case he was one of the <hi>Deputies,</hi> is by proper, and peculiar Right to be <hi>President</hi> in the forming, and constituting of the immediate <hi>Colloquie</hi> then called together to sit, and act, untill such time, as that afterwards they shall elect, and chose another: And in defalt and want of him, the <hi>President</hi> ship belongs to the Minister of the place, where the <hi>Colloquie</hi> doth assemble, by reason of the death, or absence of the former <hi>President:</hi> And so the said <hi>Colloquie</hi> being called to meet in <hi>London,</hi> the Pastor deputed for the Church of <hi>London</hi> was of right to be <hi>President</hi> in the mean time, till the rest of the Members of the <hi>Colloquie</hi> had elected another.</p>
            <p>Hereupon it fell out by course, that Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> being deputed for the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> was <hi>President</hi> for the forming, and constituting of the <hi>Colloquie:</hi> And because the rest of the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties</hi> would not promise and condescend to conjoyn with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> (before they were formed,) Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> being <hi>President</hi> as aforesaid, would not suffer the Members to form at all in <hi>Colloquie.</hi> Whereupon those other <hi>Deputies</hi> said to Mr. <hi>Stouppe, That it was not proper, or regular for one Church to command the others, and order them what they must do: For that anie one Church had as much power as the Church of</hi> London, <hi>And therefore they ought not to take to themselves singlie and apart that
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:153451:35"/>power, and priviledge, which belongs to them all in the generall.</hi> Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> perceiving that the other Churches would not do, as he would have them, rose up, and said, <hi>Let us be gone;</hi> And if I be not deceived, dissolved the Assembly without any calling upon God by prayer.</p>
            <p>The Noise, and Rumour of the dissolution of our <hi>Colloquie</hi> being conveyed to us, some fathers of families, together with Mr. <hi>Fervacques,</hi> and my self, who had all of us served as Elders, met and considered, what we should do upon these unheard of Carriages of the said <hi>Consistorie;</hi> It being on a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terday in the afternoon, and some of the <hi>Deputies</hi> having gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven out in speeches that they would return homeward on the Munday next following. And thereupon some of us resolved to go to all the <hi>Deputies</hi> and to desire them not to depart the City for some few daies; Requesting them to do the work, for which they were come up, and not to be discouraged; <hi>For we doubted not but that God in his mercie would make them Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to settle all the differences in our Church.</hi> We addressed our selves to them accordingly and told them, <hi>that the morrow being the Lords day, we intended to go to the</hi> Consistory, <hi>and desire them in the fear of God not to let the</hi> Deputies <hi>depart, till they had done their work; For which Gods providence had brought them to</hi> London <hi>to agitate.</hi> Accordingly on that <hi>Lords day</hi> we sent two of our Brethren to the <hi>Consistorie,</hi> before the first Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, desiring them to stay after Sermon, for that some fathers of families would come to propound something to them; But as soon, as the Sermon was ended, Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> went out one of the first among the people. Nevertheless we presented our selves to the <hi>Companie,</hi> desiring to speak a word, or two with them; Who desired us to come again in the afternoon; <hi>Because,</hi> as they alledged, <hi>they had no Minister;</hi> But we pressed them then to hear us, and they might report our Requests in the <hi>Consistorie</hi> in the afternoon very well; <hi>For we feared indeed that they would serve us so then in the afternoon, as they had done in the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:153451:36"/>morning.</hi> But however they would not hear us; And therefore we attended them again in the afternoon, and some of us were called in to the <hi>Consistorie;</hi> Who informed them, <hi>that our coming to them then was, upon the report, that we had heard, that our</hi> Colloquie <hi>was dissolved, whereby all our good hopes were fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strated; Desiring them in the fear of God to weigh and consider the Importance of that businesse; For as much as that they called the</hi> Colloquie <hi>to end all our differences, and there was noe reason, that they should send the</hi> Deputies <hi>away without effecting that, for which they were to assemble;</hi> And we further requested them to call them together: Whereupon they intreated us to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw, and they would give us their answer. Being with-drawn, they sent out two of their Members to us, <hi>Desiring us not stay, and they would send an answer to some of us that night.</hi> At which very instant two Elders of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Church in <hi>London,</hi> having heard how the <hi>French Consistorie</hi> had dissolved our <hi>Colloquie,</hi> came to them, <hi>desiring them likewise not to permit the</hi> Deputies <hi>to depart:</hi> Who so far prevailed with that <hi>Consistorie,</hi> as they caused them to meet again on Munday following, to try what might be done; and also they sent word to one of us, <hi>that they desired the</hi> Deputies <hi>should meet again that Munday.</hi> Who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly did meet; But the <hi>Consistorie</hi> would not at all decline, or depart from their former Resolutions: And thereupon the <hi>Deputies</hi> refused to be under their Check, or command; To which if they had summitted, they would have much injured all our Churches, and infringed, and broken our government: And the <hi>Consistorie</hi> thereupon obstinately dissolved them, and returned them their Letters of Deputation. Of which passage the <hi>Dutch Colloquie</hi> hearing the same night about eight or nine of the Clock, they thereupon sent two of their Members to all the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> Churches, <hi>Intreating them not to with-draw themselves, but that they would once more meet together:</hi> And for that purpose also desired the <hi>French Consistorie</hi> of <hi>London</hi> to depute some Members, as they themselves would do the like, that they with our <hi>Colloquie</hi> being in conference together, might
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:153451:36"/>try to obtain a right understanding between them. Upon this Proposition a meeting was procured, and something was agreed to be presented to the <hi>Dutch Colloquie</hi> to consider of. And the next day after the <hi>Deputies</hi> of our Churches, and the <hi>Consistorie</hi> presented themselves to the <hi>Dutch Colloquie;</hi> upon whom they attending in the <hi>Dutch</hi> Church, there happened a discourse between Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> and some of our <hi>Deputies;</hi> In which Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> said, that the <hi>Consistorie</hi> had ordered, that they would not defray the <hi>Deputies</hi> Charges any longer than that day. Whereupon Mr. <hi>Le Queux</hi> replyed to him, <hi>that then their businesse was at an end; For that they were deputed upon the</hi> Consistorie<hi>'s promise to defray their Charges, and since that it was so they could stay no longer; And it was in that respect but in vain to trouble the Dutch Colloquie.</hi> And hereupon Mr. <hi>Le Queux</hi> went to the <hi>Dutch Colloquie,</hi> and informed them what Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> had said. Whereupon they sent for Mr, <hi>Stouppe,</hi> and demanded, If the matter was so; Which he said, was ordered by the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistorie;</hi> And he beleived, (it being their full intention) they would not altet it. And thereby our <hi>Colloquie</hi> was absolutely dissolved.</p>
            <p>By which passages it is very easie to apprehend, that the <hi>Consistorie</hi> did not dare to come to a Triall, because they could not induce, or obtain the <hi>Deputies</hi> to act, as they would have them: For one of them said by way of Question, <hi>What reason have we to pay your Charges, If you will not do, as we would have you?</hi> Thinking that by their paying, and defraying their Charges, the <hi>Deputies</hi> ought to have done nothing, but what, and as they pleased. But as their hopes were vain, so were they therein disappointed; For some of the <hi>Deputies</hi> had bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter principles of honour and integrity, and could not be inticed to act unjustly, nor to overthrow, and destroy our govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But the <hi>Consistorie</hi> did very ill reward them for their great Love, and affection to the peace of all our Churches, who mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested the same by their coming such journeys at such an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seasonable
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:153451:37"/>time of the year,) by uttering, and vomiting out op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrious, and disgracefull speeches against them; Accusing them to be partiall to the <hi>Dutch Colloquie;</hi> And vilifying some of them with very unworthy, and unchristian expressions.</p>
            <p>True it is: It was an ungodly, and wicked Reward; but what shall we say! <hi>Can we expect an evil tree should bring forth good fruit!</hi> My expectation being thus deceived of attaining an end by our <hi>Colloquie,</hi> not long after meeting with Mr. <hi>Ʋanney</hi> (one of the Elders,) I told him, that I desired to come to an end of the difference, for that it was not well pleasing to me; Requesting him to propound to the <hi>Consistorie,</hi> that I was content to refer my business to the <hi>Dutch Consistorie</hi> to hear and determine it in the fear of God, without having any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect to persons; upon Condition that the <hi>Consistorie,</hi> and my self should first subscribe to submit to their Determination. Mr. <hi>Ʋanney</hi> accordingly presented my said proposall to them, who returned me their Answer, that they were willing to refer the Difference to a <hi>Coetus.</hi> Upon which I demanded of him, whom he meant by the word, <hi>Coetus.</hi> He answered, <hi>the Dutch and French.</hi> What? I replied, will you be judges in your own Cause? Is that just? He thereupon said to me, that if I came to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain against them, then they would with-draw. I thereupon asked him, If he thought I would not come against them? And if so, that they would depart, who then they would leave be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them? Whereto he said, <hi>The Dutch.</hi> Then I again replied, Then what difference is there, for I offered them to leave it to the <hi>Dutch Consistorie:</hi> But I suspected, that there was some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more in the business, that he did conceal from me; For that if I should have referred my self to the <hi>Coetus,</hi> &amp; then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain against the <hi>French Consistorie,</hi> and they thereupon depart from the <hi>Dutch,</hi> They would say, It could not be a <hi>Coetus</hi> without themselves; And I told him, that I beleeved, that this was their intention; And was my self of opinion, that a <hi>Coetus</hi> could not be of the <hi>Dutch</hi> onely; And therefore, they were not
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:153451:37"/>in presence with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> they would say, <hi>It was no Coetus;</hi> Wishing him not to think that they should be Parties, and Judges in their own Cause. And thereupon I resolved him, that I would send my Answer in writing to the <hi>Consistorie.</hi> And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly I conferred with Mr. <hi>Fervacques,</hi> and we agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Propositions following; Signing, and delivering them to Mr. <hi>Ʋanney,</hi> and requesting him to present them to the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistorie;</hi> which he did: The translated Copy whereof from the Originall in <hi>French</hi> I present to the Reader, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="document">
                        <head>To the Gentlemen Pastors, Elders, and Deacons of the French Church in <hi>London.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>SIRS,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                           <hi>IT hath pleased you to send to us Mr.</hi> Uanney, <hi>and Mr. to propound to us, to know, if we would condescend to referre our differences between you, and us to the</hi> Coetus:</p>
                        <p>Sirs, <hi>you are not ignorant, that we have often offered you divers waies, and means to come to a good, true, and just peace, according to the word of God, and our discipline: and we are yet of the same judgement, and desire. Therefore,</hi> Sirs, <hi>we do give this answer to your proposition, (according to our sense,) that we do not find it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, nor fitting to referre the differences to a</hi> Coetus; <hi>because it is composed of your selves, and the</hi> Dutch, <hi>and</hi> Italians: <hi>If they be a Church, it is but newly formed; So that they have no experience in our Church-government, and discipline: And moreover he that is to be their Pastor, (having been a Fryar, or a Religious man, being made so newly a Minister,) these divisions coming before him, in the first beginning of his Ministery, may be a stumbling-block, and offence and scandall to him. <hi>Sirs,</hi> To shew you, that we are very desirous to come to a good end, which shall be for the glorie of God and the good and peaceof the Church, We do propound, as followeth.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <pb n="66" facs="tcp:153451:38"/>
                        <p>
                           <hi>First, We do pray, and desire you to do your duty to the</hi> Church, <hi>that hath the order given her to call the next</hi> Colloquie; <hi>desiring them to call a</hi> Colloquie <hi>in the Spring-time, to decide, &amp; determine all the differences that have befallen from the one and the other: For it is the</hi> Colloquie, <hi>that hath right so to do; for they be our true, naturall, and onelie judges of all the differences, and unto them we have made our appeal, and to them you, and we are bound to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit: for they are the hedge, that doth <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ncompasse our Church, and they are the sinows and veins, that do nourish, and streng then the Churches, and their government, and the Phisicians to cure all the Sicknesses, and disorders: And principally it will be the means to raise up the honour of the</hi> Colloquie, <hi>that hath been troden under foot, because that they could not be suffered to form into a</hi> Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie. Sirs, <hi>These Reasons do incite us to desire you to condescend to this proposition, and we hope, that you will.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Sirs, <hi>if the above said should not be accepted, then we do propound this second, if you do judge it fit tng. It is this, If you do please to make choise of some Fathers of families of our Church, (what num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber you shall judge fitting,) and we shall choose the like number of Fathers of Families, and being agreed of the number, and of the persons, then we will draw a writing, in which we will give them full, and ample power, as anie</hi> Colloquies, <hi>or</hi> Synod <hi>have of right, to hear, and determine, and Censure; And to accomplish it from point to point.</hi> Sirs, <hi>the reason that makes us to propound this, is to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, that our disorder, and faults be no more spread abroad, then they be, to the scandall of the nation, wherein we do live.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Sirs, <hi>If the above said Propositions do not please you, we do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose this third, that is. That you, and we choose the Pastors, and El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the</hi> Dutch <hi>Church of</hi> London <hi>to be our judges, to determine upon all the Considerations, and Provisos, as they are laid down in the propositions above said; And if you please to condescend to it, then to draw out a writing according to the propositions above said, and that the one, and every one subscribe it. Then you and we
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:153451:38"/>ought to present the Agreament unto the</hi> Gentlemen <hi>of the</hi> Dutch, <hi>praying them earnestlie, that they would be pleased to accept, and undertake to decide all the differences, as above said: And by it God will be glorified, and the peace of the Church re-established; for which we desire and pray.</hi> Sirs, <hi>though we have propounded the Two last propositions, we do desire, that you would be pleased to accept the first, which is according to our duties. If one doth reject it, it seemes to us to make a breach in our discipline, and government, and dishonour to our</hi> Colloquie. Sirs, <hi>If you do not accept our</hi> Colloquie <hi>to be our judges, this shall not be drawn for an example for the time to come, nor to be prejudiciall to our</hi> Colloquies. <hi>Waiting for your answer, we rest,</hi> Sirs.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Your affectionate Brethren in the<lb/> Lord, that desire truth, &amp; peace.</hi>
                              <lb/> John Jurin <hi>Senior.</hi>
                              <lb/> Dan. Fervacques.</signed>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>London</hi>
                              <date>the 12<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>February</hi> 1655.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>The answer that we received to this our propossals from the <hi>Consistory</hi> by Mr. <hi>Ʋanney,</hi> was, <hi>That they did not reject the</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie, <hi>but would remit the business to the Coetus.</hi> Whereupon I answered, that it was an unreasonable Proposition, that they should thereby be Judges, and parties. He replyed to me, That it was the resolution of the <hi>Company.</hi> And so the Result of all was just nothing. But the Reader may be informed, that the <hi>Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story</hi> have been solicitous with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> to assume upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to be the naturall judges of all the differences: But as I understand, the <hi>Dutch</hi> would not accept of it.</p>
            <p>It hath been also propounded in the <hi>Coetus</hi> by one of the <hi>French Consistorie</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> to re-establish again a Super-inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; And another of them being in discourse with some of the <hi>Deputies</hi> of our Churches, uttered in words, That it would never be well in <hi>England,</hi> till the Bishops were again establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and these are two of the principall men, that bear sway with the plurality of the <hi>Consistorie.</hi> Whereby one may easily judge, what ill affection they bear to Reformation, since that
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:153451:39"/>they are inclined to return to the Garlick and Onyons of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and would introduce Episcopacy again, whereby they might rule, Lord, and Tyrannize over their Brethren, without any Controll.</p>
            <p>I hold it necessary, since that the Term of <hi>Coetus</hi> is so often used in this book; and thereby it might be conceived, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by some, as if it were a part of our government of our <hi>French</hi> Churches, that the Reader may be informed, and is desired to observe, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> have no power over the <hi>French,</hi> or the <hi>French</hi> over the <hi>Dutch;</hi> but are distinct from each other in their government. And if the Reader doubt any thing of the truth thereof, I referre him for full satisfaction therein to the book lately published by the Fathers of Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, whereby I hope he will be fully resolved in his judgement.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Courteous Reader</hi> may be pleased also to take notice of this following Relation, whereby he will the better discover, and discern the temper, and Constitution of Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> and his Adherents, and Abettors. And thus it was: That Mr. <hi>John Tulier</hi> having formerly served in the office of an Elder of the <hi>French</hi> Church in <hi>London,</hi> and being very much desirous, that all the differences therein might be again reconciled, did out of his great Love, and pious affection to the peace, and good of the Church, invite to his house all those persons, that had served as Elders with himself and all the present Elders, hoping to have done some good thereby: And at the beginning of their meeting did read the 13<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Chapter of 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> and afterward prayed, and then incited the <hi>Company</hi> to peace and reconciliation; And having ended his exhortation, not any one replyed. Whereupon he had us up to dinner, and in the Room were two tables set; Mr, <hi>Cisner</hi> and those that had served for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly sate at the table with Mr. <hi>Tulier,</hi> and his wife; and Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> and the present new Elders sate at the other table. When dinner was almost ended, Mr. <hi>Tulier</hi> began again to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:153451:39"/>to peace; And when he had ended, Mr. <hi>Hedlin</hi> took up the discourse, and said, that every one ought to acknowledge his fault to God, and each to other; and after that Mr. <hi>Hedlin</hi> had concluded, none took it up. Seeing that, I said, that Mr. <hi>Hedlin</hi> had propounded a true, just, and upright ground for a good, and just peace; and I said, for my part wherein I had failed, and done amiss, I would be ready to acknowledge it to God &amp; man, and doubted not, but God would give me grace so to do. Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> being sate in the Inside of the table next to M<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Tulier</hi> rose up in a very great fury and said, aloud, <hi>Sophistry, Sophistry.</hi> I said, he was a <hi>Sophister</hi> that said it. Then Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> said, I told you what it would be, let us be gone: And they all arose up in such hast, as if some great disaster was like to befall them. And Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> said a word or two of Grace, or thanks, but it was <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ery short. Mr. <hi>Tulier</hi> seeing that disorder, said, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> I pray you, as we began, so let us end; desiring Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> as he began, so that he would end. But as soon as thanks were given, Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> Mr. <hi>Stouppe,</hi> and most of the present Elders went away; But the others remained a while after. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider what an unkind reward this was to Mr. <hi>Tulier,</hi> and also whither such ungratefull guests were worthy of such an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitation. I leave the world to judge of this Carriage, whither such is the temper of wise, grave, discreet, and prudent men, fearing God.</p>
            <p>After this I understood, that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the order of the preceding <hi>Colloquie,</hi> had called a <hi>Colloquie</hi> to be held at that place on the 12th of <hi>May</hi> 1656. And thereupon I wrote to the <hi>Consistory</hi> of <hi>Canterbury</hi> in <hi>French;</hi> The translated Copy of which Letter, followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:153451:40"/>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>London <date>the 21<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of April. 1656.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>SIRS,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THe Pastors, and Elders of the <hi>French Church</hi> of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sirs, <hi>and</hi> honoured Brethren, <hi>The Cause of this is to desire you, that you would be pleased to signifie to me, if there is any hope, that there will be a</hi> Colloquie <hi>with you at the time appointed, so that I may dispose of my affairs, and be with you according to mine Appeal.</hi> Sirs, <hi>I am affraid that our</hi> Consistory <hi>endeavour what in them lies, that there be no</hi> Colloquie, <hi>and that doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage me the more, that their Cause is not good.</hi> Sirs, <hi>Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering all the waies and means, that I have used and endeavoured to come to a just end, yet notwithstanding I cannot draw them to come to the touch, to see if their actions be according to the stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard. They are verie busie in</hi> Coetus <hi>for to make them the natural</hi> Judges; <hi>But the</hi> Gentlemen <hi>of the</hi> Dutch <hi>will not accept it on those terms: yet however they have voted in</hi> Coetus, <hi>that they are competent</hi> Judges. <hi>But me thinks! they needed not to have done it, for it would have been more for their honour to have stayed, till that they had been chosen to be such.</hi> Sirs, <hi>it is too manifest that the</hi> Consistory <hi>hath a good will to break our government, and to re-establish again a Super-intendent; for one of them hath made that proposition in</hi> Coetus; <hi>But the</hi> Gentlemen <hi>of the</hi> Dutch <hi>took no knowledge of it. So that one may easily judge by what Spirit they are lead. But I doubt not, but in a short time God will again raise up, the honour of our</hi> Colloquies <hi>in despite of the enemies thereof, and will make them appear to the world such as they are, and render to them according to their deserts.</hi> Sirs, <hi>I do desire you, that you would excuse me, that I have so much enlarged my self. Waiting your answer, I do remain.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Sirs,</salute>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your affectionate servant,</hi>
                        <lb/> John Jurin <hi>Senior.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:153451:40"/>
            <p> By some mishap I cannot now find the Letter it self, which was sent to me from <hi>Canterbury</hi> in Answer; And therefore I shall not further enlarge my self thereupon.</p>
            <p>By the aforesaid ill behaviours of the <hi>Consistory</hi> of <hi>London</hi> all our hopes were even at an end: But unexpectedly the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> having the charge given them by the last preceding <hi>Colloquie,</hi> that they should call another on the 12th of <hi>May</hi> in the year. 1656, as aforesaid, did accordingly do the same; And thereby our hopes began in some measure to revive, and renew in us. And the better to effect, and bring to passe the meeting of a <hi>Colloquie,</hi> the fathers of families (before mentioned) made application to the said <hi>Consistory</hi> of <hi>London;</hi> requesting them, that they would be pleased to put to their helping hand, that the <hi>Colloquie</hi> might be assembled at the time appointed: But instead of assording their assistance, they did, (as it seems,) rather endeavour to hinder it; For the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Canterbury</hi> could receive no Answer at all from them, till such time as a second Letter was sent by one of the Elders there to an Elder in <hi>London;</hi> And wherefore there was no <hi>Colloquie</hi> at all, the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Canterbury</hi> are more able to demonstrate, than my self: And thereupon I shall forbear to enlarge my self in any thing, but rather proceed to other particulars conducing to a greater, and more plain Discovery of the truth. Yet one thing may be worthy of the Readers Enquiry, for what Cause Mr. <hi>Du Perrier,</hi> (who now officiates as a Minister in the <hi>French</hi> Church at <hi>Southampton,</hi> and yet hath no other Ordination, than of a priest in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> wherein he took his Orders, and therefore ought not by our Discipline, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to be admitted, or received into any of our Churches) did come over from the <hi>Isle</hi> of <hi>Garnsay</hi> into <hi>England;</hi> And when the <hi>Consistory</hi> of <hi>London</hi> obstructed, and prevented the form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our <hi>Colloquie</hi> before mentioned, they then shewed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves very kind, and courteous to the said Mr. <hi>Du Perrier,</hi> lending to him ten pounds in money, to be repaid to them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:153451:41"/>when he shall obtain an Augmentation to be laid to his Pastor-ship from some <hi>English</hi> living.</p>
            <p>This may be said for further satisfaction of the Reader, that some other of our <hi>French</hi> Churches, being so notoriously af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted, and evilly entreated by the <hi>Consistory</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> were wholly discouraged, and had no great desires to meet in <hi>Colloquie,</hi> conceiving they could do little, or no good. And so no <hi>Colloquie</hi> assembling, the said <hi>Consistory</hi> proceded more and more to trample all the rest of their Brethren (as it were) under foot. Which Ambition of theirs constrained some Fathers of Families, who (having made divers offers and Proposalls for peace according to our Discipline, but all were rejected by the <hi>Consistory,</hi>) could discover no other waies, or means of Redress, humbly to make their Address to his <hi>Highness</hi> the Lord <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector.</hi> And after some time spent, they by his gracious favour obtained a <hi>Colloquie,</hi> that they should meet and determine all our Differences.</p>
            <p>But a little while before such Relief was prayed from his <hi>Highness,</hi> Mr. <hi>John D'oneau</hi> came from <hi>Canterbury</hi> to <hi>London:</hi> Concerning whom the <hi>Consistory</hi> of <hi>London</hi> had given out in speeches, <hi>that he was run away,</hi> and would not appear before them. Of whose Coming Mr. <hi>Fervacques</hi> having knowledge, acquainted me therewith: Desiring (in respect of that Asper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion) that we might go to some of the <hi>Consistory,</hi> and give them notice of Mr. <hi>D'oneau</hi>'s presence in <hi>London;</hi> for that he was the same day, or the next morning to return to <hi>Norwich.</hi> Wherefore we being at the Exchange, did inform Mr. <hi>Isaac L'il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> (one of the Elders,) <hi>of</hi> Mr. D'onean'<hi>s being in town, who had testified against</hi> Mr. Cisner: <hi>And being the</hi> Consistory <hi>had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merlie said, that he was run away, and durst not shew himself,</hi> they might do well to speak with him. He answered, <hi>that he could not do it of himself, for that he might in so doing be censured.</hi> We therefore desired him to speak with some of his Brethren: And
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:153451:41"/>at the very instant we espied another of the <hi>Consistory;</hi> request<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mr. <hi>De Lillers</hi> to go to him, and consider of it, and return us their Resolution presently, for that Mr. <hi>D'oneau</hi> having earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est business at <hi>Colchester,</hi> was to be gone that night or next morning early, that he might be at that place on Saturday night. But at that Exchange-time they gave us no Answer: But after dinner they sent to Mr. <hi>Fervacques,</hi> that Mr. <hi>D'oneau</hi> should come to Mr. <hi>Bar</hi>'s house about five of the Clock that afternoone.</p>
            <p>I told Mr. <hi>Fervacques,</hi> that as I did believe, if they were wise, the Members of the <hi>Consistory</hi> would not meet with Mr. <hi>D'oneau</hi> at the place appointed; For that there might, or would be some new matter, or evidence discovered. But when the hour was come, Mr. <hi>Fervacques</hi> together with Mr. <hi>Du'quesne,</hi> and Mr. <hi>D'oneau</hi> did go to Mr. <hi>Bar</hi>'s house, leaving notice thereof for me at my house; upon which I did immediately repair thither. Where being come, the party of the <hi>Consistory</hi> would have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suaded Mr. <hi>D'oneau</hi> to go into another Room, wherein Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> and some Elders were met together: For that Mr. <hi>Bar</hi> said, <hi>there were other persons besides</hi> Mr. D'oneau; <hi>And things would be otherwise reported, than they really were.</hi> Whereupon Mr. D'<hi>oneau</hi> replied, that he gave him a good Caution, and therefore he would not speak any thing, but in presence of Witnesses: Upon which Mr. <hi>Bar</hi> pressed him to come on the Lords-day following to the <hi>Consistory:</hi> But he said, he could not stay so long, for that he was to be at <hi>Colchester</hi> on the Saturday night: But if that in case he could stay, he resolved not to speak any thing before them, unless there were more persons present, than at that time were attending to bear witness.</p>
            <p>It so fell out at that time, that we could by no means prevail with Mr. <hi>Bar,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Isaac De Lillers,</hi> that Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> Mr. <hi>D'obey,</hi> (and as I think) some others of them then present, that they and we together in person should hear what Mr. <hi>D'oneau</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:153451:42"/>would testifie: But instead thereof they unworthily taxed us, that things would be falsely reported. To prevent which, we propounded, that whatsoever should be said by one, or the other party, should be written down and signed, and affirmed by ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: But this would nothing at all move them; And therefore I wished them, that they should not give out any more in speeches, that Mr. <hi>D'oneau</hi> durst not shew his face; But that they would rather acknowledge, that Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> durst not shew his. But indeed Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> may be accounted wise to disappear, for if he, and Mr. <hi>D'oneau</hi> had come face to face, no doubt, but that Mr. <hi>D'oneau</hi> would have revealed some other particulars, than what he had done before; And besides there would have been more Witnesses to his Relation, than formerly. But being we could not induce them to a personall meeting, (as before is mentioned to be desired by us,) we took our leave, and departed: Yet further as I told those <hi>Gentlemen</hi> of the <hi>Consistory,</hi> that if it had been my case, as it was Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi>'s, that Mr. <hi>D'oneau</hi> should (as Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> said) have related a false thing of me, I would have sought him, If he had been to have been found above ground: But certainly, when Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> fully knew, that Mr. <hi>D'oneau</hi> was in the same house with him according to his appointment, and Expectation (or else why came he thither?) and yet he would not speak with him; It must needs declare him to be guilty of what Mr. <hi>D'oneau</hi> had accused him. For if he could have cleared, and vindicated his innocence, We should for our parts have been very glad there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and also desirous, that Mr. <hi>D'oneau</hi> in making his first re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to Mr. <hi>Fervacques,</hi> whereby to traduce and scandalize Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> should therefore have suffered due Censure, and Reproof; As well we may expect, that Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> should yet undergo the same, for his being backward, and averse to give sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for his offence, of which he plainly stands convicted by his silence, and obstinacy.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Reader</hi> shall further discern the rancour, and obstinate
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:153451:42"/>behaviour of the <hi>Consistory</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> who, when that his <hi>Highnesse</hi> had graciously granted us (as before I have related) the Liberty of a <hi>Colloquie,</hi> did neverthelesse petition against it; Accusing them unworthily to be partiall, and falsely affirming, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> were our naturall Judges: Which petition they prosecuting at <hi>White-Hall</hi> with much earnestness, at the length some Fathers of Families (with my self) being by Gods good Providence at that place, and discovering their Attendance, were at length on both parties called in before his <hi>Highnesse;</hi> where, upon his <hi>Highnesse</hi> heating the Allegations on both sides, those <hi>Gentlemen</hi> in the end confessed, that the <hi>Colloquies</hi> composed of the Members of our own <hi>French</hi> Churches, were our proper judges; and also professed, that they were never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them; promising before his <hi>Highnesse,</hi> that a <hi>Colloquie</hi> should assemble. Concerning the time of whose meeting, and the manner thereof, and how they were not rightly constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, nor did regularly act, being they were but five persons, and all of them not properly qualified, &amp; also were disclaimed and disowned by six other lawfull <hi>Deputies,</hi> and the <hi>Consisto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> of severall Churches, I shall herein forbear to relate, but do referre the Reader to the Book of the Fathers of Families before mentioned, being a Refutation of a book before printed by the <hi>Consistory.</hi> But give me leave to inform you, so farre as I was my self concerned at the meeting of that pretended <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie,</hi> (for so I must call it,) in as much as his <hi>Highnesse,</hi> and our Churches were abused, <hi>viz:</hi> himself in his pious, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Intentions, and our selves in our Discipline, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; And so I shall make my progress to declare the truth, and nothing else.</p>
            <p>Those five persons under the notion, and pretence of a <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie</hi> about two daies before their Dissolution sending for me, as soon as I had but notice I appeared before them; Desiring to know for what Cause they had sent for me. They said, to demand of me, If that I had any thing <hi>against the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:153451:43"/>Consistory of London.</hi> I answered, <hi>yes,</hi> and <hi>also against</hi> Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> in particular: But I told them, <hi>that I did see but onely five per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of them sitting, who could not make up a Colloquie.</hi> They said, that they were six, yet I could see (as again I affirmed) but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly five. Whereupon they replied, that there was an Elder come from <hi>Dover,</hi> &amp; was here by eight of the Clock that morning, and that he was then admitted. I said to them that it was very strange to me, for that Elder, that was chosen by that Church, and sent up to <hi>London,</hi> and being newly come, did by Constraint de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part again from thence homewards by reason of his <hi>Highnesse</hi>'s Proclamation, for that he had born Arms against the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. This was on the Saturday at noone that I appeared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, and that Elder left the City but the Thursday night late before, and could not be at <hi>Dover</hi> at soonest, before the night following; On which night I beleeved both the <hi>Consisto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> there had not met together to make a new choice, (in case they were informed of the necessity of the cause) to give him a Letter of Deputation, which could not in any possibility be here by that Saturday morning by eight of the Clock; Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I desired them, that they would be pleased to receive Mr. <hi>Le Queux,</hi> and his Elder deputed from <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and then I would proceed to declare against Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> and our <hi>Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story.</hi> They answered, that Mr. <hi>Le Queux</hi> might come, if he would: I desired again, that both he and his Elder might be received, for then they would be the plurality of our Churches, and then I would declare my Complaint: Forasmuch as, that albeit they were six persons rightly qualified; Yet not being the greater part of the <hi>Deputies</hi> of all our Churches, they could not be properly a well constituted <hi>Colloquie.</hi> And this passage was on the Saturday afore mentioned after twelve of the Clock; At which time I left the <hi>Company,</hi> and repaired to the Exchange, where I met with Mr. <hi>Le Queux,</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted him with what I had said to them, and what was the <hi>Companie</hi>'s Answer to me: He assured me, <hi>that he and his Elder would attend them at two of the Clock that afternoone, to try
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:153451:43"/>what they would do;</hi> And they did so: But the <hi>Company</hi> would not receive either of them. By which may well be collected, how light, and triviall a matter they accounted it, to tell an untruth, whereby to deceive their brother. Immediately after at the same Exchange-time on the Saturday aforesaid, meeting with one of the Elders sitting (as in a <hi>Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie,</hi>) at that place, I asked him, <hi>how it could be possible, that they had received another Elder from</hi> Dover <hi>so quickly;</hi> Who an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered me, <hi>That the Minister of</hi> Dover <hi>did choose him, and the</hi> Colloquie <hi>approved of him.</hi> Whereupon I demanded of him, <hi>whither this was according to our Discipline and Government: For that the right of the Choice is by the Minister, Elders, and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons of the</hi> Consistory, <hi>and without them together no</hi> Deputy <hi>could be chosen to be sent to the</hi> Colloquie: I said also to him, <hi>that I did marvell to see things, carried altogether so contrary to all Rule and Government; whereby I did see, that they had a minde to destroy our good Government.</hi> And thereupon I desired of him, that I might know, <hi>who it was, that was so newly chosen:</hi> To which he gave me answer, <hi>that it was</hi> Mr. <hi>De Haze.</hi> On which I said to him, <hi>that that person had been a good while in the City, and was then no Elder at that present at</hi> Dover, <hi>&amp; was also</hi> Mr. Cisner<hi>'s Brother in law, and the very man, that preferred</hi> Mr. Cisner <hi>to our Church in</hi> London; <hi>whereby in truth one might easily see, how unrighteously they walked, and that none could expect a blessing from their procedings, because they did behave themselves fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On which Saturday the <hi>Deputies</hi> of the Church of <hi>Santhoff</hi> arrived in <hi>London;</hi> And on the Munday morning following the Minister of that place (to wit) Mr. <hi>Kerhuel,</hi> (his Elder being not well at his Inne,) presented himself singly to the <hi>Company;</hi> And the same time also Mr. <hi>Le Queux</hi> and his Elder, present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themselves to be received: But the pretended <hi>Colloquie</hi> told them, they were not a <hi>Colloquie</hi> at the present, but desired them to come again in the after noone; After those aforesaid were
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:153451:44"/>dismissed, then the Fathers of Families and the four Deacons, and my self presented our selves to them; Intending to have desired of them to receive the above said, and then we would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare. But we desiring to speak with them they told us, that they were not a <hi>Colloquie,</hi> but desired us to come again to them in the after-noone. So all we the above-said attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them again at that time, and waited a long time upon them; and at length they sent to all of us word, that they were not a <hi>Colloquie,</hi> because one of them was wanting, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired us to come to them again the next morning. Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly we all appeared as appointed; And then they called in Mr. <hi>Le Queux,</hi> and his Elder, but would not admit them to their <hi>Company.</hi> They also called in Mr. <hi>Kerhuel,</hi> (whose Elder was not well in health,) telling him, that they could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him, for three Reasons, <hi>viz.</hi> First, <hi>Because he had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved imposition of hands by</hi> English Ministers; Secondly, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause there was not written on the Top of his Letters of Deputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> (A Messeurs, Les Messeurs the Ministers and Elders in Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie.) Thirdly, Because he was come too <hi>late with his</hi> Elder, <hi>for that they had almost done.</hi> He desired earnestly to be received, whereby he might joyn with them to strengthen them, and confirm such Acts, as were just, and right. They denyed him, saying they could not. Thereupon the Fathers of Families, the four Deacons, and my self presented our selves to them; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>questing them to receive the said two Churches, there being then sufficient persons enough to constitute a <hi>Colloquie.</hi> And that on the morrow the Church of <hi>Thorney-Abbey</hi> would also be with them; And then the <hi>Colloquie</hi> would be composed of all the Churches; Pressing them, that we might be heard, what we had to say, whereby an end might be made of our unhappy, and ungodly Differences. Upon this they desired us to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw, and being a while with-drawn, they did rise, and depart, with out calling us in again; but sent to us the Minister of <hi>Dover,</hi> who informed us, <hi>that they could not proceed, because that we stood for a full</hi> Colloquie. Then we suspected, they were dissolved
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:153451:44"/>and therefore we urged him to let us know, whither the <hi>Colloquie</hi> was dissolved; To which he would not return any Answer. And as farre as we could discover from some others of them, the <hi>Colloquie</hi> (as they pretended themselves to be) at that very instant <hi>(being Tuesday before noone)</hi> did absolutely dissolve.</p>
            <p>With most fervent desire I beseech the <hi>Courteous Reader</hi> to consider the order, and manner of procedings of the aforesaid five men, who did take upon themselves the name of a <hi>Colloquie,</hi> when as they were not the plurality of our Churches; And with all to observe the falseness, and deceipt of their Answer at their breaking up, imparted to us by the Minister of <hi>Dover.</hi> For asmuch as that they did nevertheless before their Departure confirm the three Acts, made by the <hi>Consistory</hi> of <hi>London</hi> wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully against Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> and also pass other pretended Acts against the Fathers of Families, (As is more amply related in their aforesaid Book,) keeping them secret, without sending for any of the parties concerned, whereby to admonish, and persuade them by Reasons significant, that they would submit to their Sentences, or otherwise they would make them publick to the People in the Pulpit. But on the contrary, and in a most unchristian manner they did the next Lords day after publish them in the Pulpit; Although they had told us, that they could not proceed, because we stood for a full <hi>Colloquie.</hi> I pray the Reader to observe this ungodly dealing!</p>
            <p>Also I intreat the <hi>Benevolent Reader</hi> to take notice of the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of our Churches; which is, that every <hi>Consistory</hi> of each particular Church must have the Major part of the Ministers and Elders, whereby to make them capable to Act, as a <hi>Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story.</hi> Much more rather then (I say) ought a <hi>Colloquie</hi> to be composed of the plurality of <hi>Deputies</hi> of our Churches at the least; And indeed by our government, they ought all to be present from all the Churches, whereby the Major part of them
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:153451:45"/>might have the affirmative, or Negative votes; As more fully appears by the aforesaid book of the Fathers of Families. But from hence may be drawn into an unquestionable Argument, that the procedings of those five persons were so farre without example, as that the like hath not been heard of in any reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches, throughout the world; And in it self most plainly contradictory to our common practice in the ordinary exercise of our Discipline, and government: For that we never use to publish any Sentence to the disgrace of any offender whatsoever by name, though for never so gross a sin at the first; nay, nor untill after three severall Admonitions to persuade them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and Amendment. And of this I will vouch a late Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent in our Church, which is this; that a woman (a Member of the same) running away from her husband with another man, the <hi>Consistory</hi> published onely, that a sister (without name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her) had committed a foule sinne. But these <hi>Gentlemen</hi> without any Consideration, immediately (as aforesaid) make a publication by name of their brethren, as offendors. But well we may say, they might do it, for that (right, or wrong,) one of them said to Mr. <hi>Le Queux, Whatsoever they did they must save the honour of the Consistory:</hi> And Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> himself said amongst them, (desiring them to make hast) <hi>that if the other Churches did come, his Consistory would be undone.</hi> And another <hi>Deputie</hi> affirmed, <hi>that it would never be well in the Churches, till there were Bishops again.</hi> But it is to be considered further in what Post-hast these <hi>Gentlemen</hi> made their progress, when they heard, and plainly did see, that two Churches were here, and the last on their journey, and the next day would attend them; And if they had had that good affection to the peace of the Church, as they should have had in love to justice, and truth, they would have received them all, though they had stayd two, or three daies longer; Whereby to have the judgement, and consent of all the other Churches together with themselves. But I must confess, well weighing the Experience of these five <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> (for three of them never were in a <hi>Colloquie</hi> before,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:153451:45"/>and the other two not in many,) they were nimble, to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch such weighty matters in so very short a time: However I shall say, that for what concerned me, or Mr. <hi>Fervaeques</hi> they did not any thing therein. The reasons wherefore they did not, I conceive may be, either For that two other Churches were here already, aad the other of <hi>Thorney-Abbey</hi> would be with them on the next Wednesday morning, or that they were conscious to themselves that the business against Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> and <hi>Consistory,</hi> was very foul.</p>
            <p>After the departure of these five per sons, there was severall Overtures, and proffers for peace used by the Fathers of Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and my self (As in their book is related more at large) to the <hi>Consistory</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> whereby to appease our Differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, I finding no other Remedy, did pen this ensuing Adress to them in <hi>French,</hi> And Indevoured to deliver it unto the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory</hi> by my Elder, but they knowing that it came from me, they would not receive it. So that I was constrained to Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried it my self to them &amp; with much a do I obtained leave to read it in their presence, the translation whereof I render you, <hi>vix.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>London <date>the 7<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of Octo. 1657.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <head>Superscription. To Messaurs the Pastors, Elders, and Deacons of the French Church in London.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIRS,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YOu are not ignorant of the severall propositions which I have offered to you from time to time; hoping, that they would have Induced you to have put a finall end to the difference befallen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:153451:46"/>
                     <hi>Mr. Cisner,</hi> you and my self. Seeing that it hath continued so long a time, and that there is nothing done in it; And the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est evil is, that there is no hope of the doing of it; seeing that our Churches are so torn and devided on against the other, so that we cannot have a <hi>Colloquie,</hi> that may cure our evil in the Estate into which they are put, The which is the greatest judgement of God that hath befallen them since their being in this nation, And that ought to be unto us matter of great humiliation before God, And all true Christians that have the glorie of God in singular recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation and the good and the peace of our Churches; they ought to study how they may bring water to quench this Inflamed fire. And I conceive this Obligation is principally upon you because of the solemn promise that you have made unto God in the face of the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the which I do pray you well to consider. <hi>Sirs,</hi> I do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that it is also my dutie, Therefore to testifie the very great desire that I have that the above said difference be decided in the fear of God; I do conceive that such a way may yet be found out, if it pleased God so to Incline all our hearts unto such a just and holy resolution. So that truth and peace might imbrace each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it proceeding from a heart truely humbled in sincerity, so thereby God will be glorified. <hi>Sirs,</hi> the proposition that I desire to propose unto you is: That there be very manie <hi>English</hi> Ministers in this Citie that are pious and fearing God, and that are of the same government with us. I say <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and that have not taken part with the one or with the other partie; so that they may be Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent judges, In giving them full and ample power, that the <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquies</hi> have of right for to examine and determine the difference between you and me. And I say that I will submit unto them with heart and affection, not doubting but they will give sentence ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to equitie and justice, so by the blessing of God it may be the first step to bring one peace even unto all the other differences In the Church. <hi>Sirs,</hi> I hope that God will incline you to accept of this proposition; praying you to Consider it maturely in his fear, so to prevent the increase of the evil between you and I for if you will not remit the decision of it unto persons not Interessed and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:153451:46"/>fearing God; you will Oblidge me to do that which ought not to be done in following your own steps: <hi>I</hi> say in that which is truth for my justification unto all the world, praying you to prevent it and to Condescend unto that which is just, and right before God and men. And desiring you to do me that favour as to send me your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer in writing for which I wait and rest.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your brother that desires nothing<lb/> else but truth and peace.</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi>John Jurin</hi> Senior.</signed> Superscribed.<lb/>
                     <salute>To Messeurs the Pastors, Elders, and Deacons of the <hi>French</hi> Church in <hi>London.</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>On the 14<seg rend="sup">th</seg> day of the said moneth of <hi>October</hi> last past I read the foregoing Address to the <hi>Company</hi> of our <hi>Consistory,</hi> and because they refused my proffer therein, I thereupon presented my self with the following Second Application made to them in <hi>French</hi> with new matters proposed, And wherein you will see their answer to my former, The traslation whereof I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to the Readers perusall, as it followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="address">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>London <date>the 21<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of Octo. 1657.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Sirs, The Pastors Elders and Deacons.</salute>
                           <salute>Sirs,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>THere is now <hi>8<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
                           </hi> daies since that I prrsented my self unto you with my Letter of the <hi>7<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
                           </hi> of this present and at length I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained permition of you to read it the which was adressed unto you,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:153451:47"/>and presented unto you by <hi>Mr. Tainturier</hi> the last Lords day. But would not receive it because you understand that it came from me In the which Letter I did labour to stir you up very much to condecend that a final end might be put unto the difference befallen between <hi>Mr. Cisner</hi> you and my self, and for that end I made this proposition, That you would be pleased to remit the said difference unto some goodly and pious <hi>English</hi> Ministers of the same judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and government with us, But that proposition did not please you saying, that that was against our Discipline and government, And that this example might be of evil Consequence for the fewtor. <hi>Sirs,</hi> I do conceive that the said proposition is not In any thing contrary unto our Discipline as I told you then. So I say again and if you can shew me anie act of Discipline or <hi>Colloquie</hi> that hath the least shew of dislike of it I will not Insist anie more upon it, And then I told you seeing that you cannot shew me any such act that shew dislike of it. Therefore <hi>I</hi> said I will produce unto you a example to shew you that it may be done even of our times In the Cause of <hi>Mr. Cisner.</hi> Where was chosen by Consent of both parts <hi>English Scotch Dutch</hi> &amp; <hi>French</hi> Ministers. Thought they could not do anie thing therein, but left it as they found it, and neverless <hi>I</hi> have not heard of anie of the partes that were sensured by the preceding <hi>Colloquies</hi> for their yeilding unto such a expedient. <hi>Sirs,</hi> The answer that <hi>Mr. Stouppe</hi> gave me was, may be the <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie</hi> had forgotten to do it, and also <hi>Mr. Stouppe</hi> said to me that the <hi>Company</hi> was content to remit it unto the <hi>Coetus.</hi> Then I said unto you that it seemed unto me unjust, for you will be judges and parties; and also <hi>I</hi> told you that the <hi>Coetus</hi> was joyned with them. In the petition to his hight against the <hi>Colloquie</hi> and that <hi>Mr. Callundrine</hi> was with them to promote the delivering the petition so that they made themselves parties with you, so that they cannot be competent judges. I acknowledge that one of you said that when the businesse should be debated In <hi>Coetus</hi> you would with draw. But <hi>Mr. Cisner</hi> said the contrary as he did not long since In <hi>Coetus,</hi> when they were prayed that they would make the tenth appear; of the testimonie they gave unto our <hi>Consistory</hi> which
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:153451:47"/>they have delivered to his height? Then we Complained that they did us wrong In suffering our <hi>Consistory</hi> to sit with them, seeing that they were parties; &amp; now judges which is unjusti<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>. You know very well that <hi>Mr. Cisner</hi> was there president, and he said that they ought not to with-draw. And if they did with-draw, they were no <hi>Coetus:</hi> and not on of the <hi>Company</hi> did again say it. So that it is to apparent that <hi>Mr. Cisner</hi> dares not trust his and your cause unto anie persons to decide the difference; unless you are judges and parties, I say that it is unjustice. <hi>Sirs,</hi> seeing that there is no hope to have a <hi>Colloquie</hi> according to our Discipline in our daies. Because of the great afronts that you have done unto them; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for the last time, I do propose unto you another expedient and that is this. That I do leave it unto you to chouse such persons as you shall think good. Ʋpon Condition that I have the same libertie; And to give unto them full and ample power, that the <hi>Colloquies</hi> have of right for to examine the on and the others; and that all books and Letters, and Papers, shall be delivered them that they shall require. So that they may come to a final sentence, according to the demerits of the Cause; and that one and every one do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise to submit unto that they shall ordain. And in case that those <hi>Gentlemen</hi> that are chosen by the one and the other, could not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree they shall have power to make choise of some other person for to joyn with them; so by that means to make a final end. <hi>Sirs,</hi> me thinks one should do well not to make choise of anie persons that is Interessed in the devision; for in so doing there will be no end. But rather to take persons: that have had no knowledge of it, and this seem unto me the most sclide way to end it; hoping that you will accept the one or the other of these propositions, for to prevent that which will remain unto posteritie, so waiting for your answer I rest.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Him that desires nothing else<lb/> but truth and peace.</hi>
                              <lb/>
                              <hi>John Jurin</hi> Senior.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:153451:48"/>
            <p> The afore recited Address I read to the <hi>Consistory</hi> the said 21<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>October,</hi> last past. And their Answer was, <hi>that if I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented my self according to the Discipline they would hear me. And that the future they would not suffer papers to be read unto them.</hi> So by this they take away from me all the means that I have to utter my thought because that I have not the <hi>French</hi> so per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly as to express my self Receiving this short, and insuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Answer from them, and no other satisfaction, or repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this day, and having no other mean left me, whereby to vindicate my self from their unjust aspersions cast upon me, and their wrongfull suspension of me from the Lords Supper, (when as I did onely contend to clear my self from Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi>'s false Accusation, the matter wherewith I did seem to reprove him, being so fully justified at the very first by Mr. <hi>Fervacques</hi> to have been by him related to me, and at the length testified by Mr. <hi>D'oncau</hi> to be certainly true, and more particuliarly is manifested by Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> one Letter; how treacheriously and Judas like he hath dealt with Mr. <hi>De Laune</hi> and his Church, and especially with our <hi>Colloquie</hi> that Imployed him in that Deputation, which doth represent all our Churches. So that that Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> hath betrayed all our Churches; I therefore caused this Relation of all Circumstances, and particulars from first to last to be imprinted, and communicated to the publick view of the world, but especially of those <hi>Gentlemen</hi> to whom I have made my dedication hereof, and all Juditious, and well willing Christians, whose favour shall be so farre extended to me, as to be well pleased to read and compare this book; Not doubting, but that their Consideration thereof will regularly lead, and induce to a just judgement, and positive vindication of me in the premisses; And I hope in the end, that Almighty God will be graciously pleased to administer a fitting Redress, whereby I may be justly vindicated. And that those persons who have acted against me with so much unreasonableness, and Inconsideration, and directly contrary to the Discipline and government of all our Churches, in suspending me, as a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:153451:48"/>may have that Censure and reproof, as the Acts, Articles, and Constitutions of our government have provided and esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished.</p>
            <p>For the Conclusion of this my Narrative, I desire the <hi>Reader</hi> to observe, that I have been credibly informed, that Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> hath very lately preached; <hi>That the Law is holy, just and good,</hi> calling God and the Angells to bear witness, that he never preached against the <hi>Law,</hi> or ever called it an <hi>Hypocrite</hi> or the like; Whereas it will be abundantly <hi>proved</hi> by very many wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses (then Auditors); That Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> almost two years since did in two severall Sermons publickly preach against the <hi>holy Law</hi> of God, and since that time maintained the same unto private persons: The first time that he so preached, some (then present) were much offended, especial<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y Mr. <hi>Beaumont,</hi> who went the next day to <hi>his Elder</hi> and complained thereof desiring him that he would entreat Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> to give him satisfaction therein, but all in vain; For in another Sermon, (he having been questioned for the former) was so farr from giving the least of satisfaction, that he <hi>maintained</hi> what he had so delivered with much more vigour then before, so that very many more were much offended thereat, and made their severall complaints unto their respective <hi>Elders</hi> desiring that Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> might give them satisfaction either by <hi>maintaining</hi> that his false and erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious doctrine, or by <hi>disclaiming</hi> it; but nothing could be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured from him accordingly.</p>
            <p>Now let the <hi>Reader</hi> judge, whether this be the way for any true <hi>Gospel Minister</hi> to take, as first to preach Atheisticall and blasphemous doctrine against the <hi>Majesty of God,</hi> and his most <hi>holy Law;</hi> Then to cover his sin, because he cannot make it good by the <hi>word of truth;</hi> Lasty, to be so impiously wicked, as to dare to call God and his Angells to <hi>justifie</hi> him in all his wickednesses. But to close up all, thus much I dare be bold to affirm, and that upon good warrant too, That if he doth not <hi>repent,</hi> God and his own Conscience will be a terrible <hi>Witness</hi> against him one day.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>